<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Screencast | That TDD Fellow | Tech Blog | Screencasts]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/categories/screencast/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-30T00:29:56+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oleksii Fedorov (waterlink)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD #6: Continuous Integration Training]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/08/10/tdd-screencast-number-6-continuous-integration-training/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-10T19:35:41+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/08/10/tdd-screencast-number-6-continuous-integration-training</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/178357638" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/178357638">Test-Driven Development Screencast #6: Continuous Integration Training</a></p>

<p><em>(Recommended to watch full-screen and HD: 720p or more)</em></p>

<p>List of all TDD Screencasts can be <a href="/blog/categories/tdd-screencasts/">found here</a>.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Today we are going to discuss Continuous Integration, what it is and what it isn&rsquo;t. We will define best Check-Out/Check-In cycle. We will explore ways to train our Continuous Integration skills. And we will do some live coding on Kata with special restriction, that allows one to train such skills. Then we will draw a bottom line.</p>

<p>Thanks for watching! If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don&rsquo;t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD #5: English Numbers Kata]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/06/19/tdd-number-5-english-numbers-kata/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-19T18:41:39+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/06/19/tdd-number-5-english-numbers-kata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/171307899?color=c9ff23" width="640" height="360" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/171307899">Test-Driven Development Screencast #5: English Numbers Kata</a></p>

<p><em>(Recommended to watch full-screen and HD: 720p or more)</em></p>

<p>List of all TDD Screencasts can be <a href="/blog/categories/tdd-screencasts/">found here</a>.</p>

<p>This screencast was born from my previous blog post: <a href="/blog/2016/05/27/iterative-divide-and-conquer-or-how-to-solve-problems/">Iterative Divide &amp; Conquer or How to solve problems</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD #4: Path Finding]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/13/tdd-number-4-path-finding/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-13T09:56:15+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/13/tdd-number-4-path-finding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/DTzhlNIjWRY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Recommended to watch in a full-screen and on 720p or higher quality.</p>

<p>List of all TDD Screencasts can be <a href="/blog/categories/tdd-screencasts/">found here</a>.</p>

<h2>Script</h2>

<p>Hello. I am Oleksii Fedorov and I am wearing a hat of That TDD Fellow. That
means you are watching TDD Screencast episode #4.</p>

<p>As mentioned in the previous episode, today we are going to implement a path
finding algorithm.</p>

<p>Specifically, our first problem in a path finding theme will be the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>We are given a directional graph, that consists of nodes and edges between
them.</li>
<li>We are given two nodes: start and finish.</li>
<li>We need to answer such questions:

<ul>
<li>Is there a path from start to finish?</li>
<li>If there is, What this path is?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>I need to make a remark, that we clearly dont have to return the shortest path,
just any path, that we can find. We will tackle shortest path problem in later
episodes.</p>

<p>Now, I think we can start.</p>

<pre><code>./watch.sh
vim         # coding session
</code></pre>

<p>This was pretty easy to make a DFS algorithm to emerge on its own, by driving
it with the specification. Lets see if it is possible to do the same with
shortest path problem.. Next time, on the TDD Screencast. Have a nice day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[TDD #3: Kind Sort]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/04/tdd-number-3-kind-sort/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-04T01:16:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/04/tdd-number-3-kind-sort</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TR2hKaR4zg8" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Recommended to watch in a full-screen and on 720p or higher quality.</p>

<h2>Script</h2>

<p>Hello, hello! I am Oleksii Fedorov, and this is the third
episode of TDD Screencast.</p>

<p>In last episode we have implemented a sorting algorithm
using TDD, without thinking about algorithm beforehand. As a
result, bubble sort have emerged.</p>

<p>We have noticed, that there is a small weird thing about
this implementation: it has unspecified behavior - mutation
of the original array.</p>

<p>So we asked, which algorithm would emerge, if we were to ban
such side-effects from our algorithm. Let&rsquo;s find out!</p>

<pre><code>./watch.sh
vim           # implement sorting algorithm
</code></pre>

<p>I think we are done here. If you look closely, it is a
quicksort. It is not the most memory-efficient
implementation, but that is something that is simple to
optimize (instead of passing recursively arrays, pass
original array and indexes). That optimization will involve
actual mutation of the array in place, so if we want to stay
true to our specification /show test for no-side-effects/.
We will have to copy the array once, using some sort of
wrapper function.</p>

<p>Applying this optimization I leave as an exercise to you my
users.</p>

<p>In the next episode we will look into path-finding problem,
and we will see, how these techniques apply there. See you
next time! Have a nice day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Test-Driven-Development Screencast #2]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/02/test-driven-development-screencast-number-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-02-02T08:28:14+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/02/02/test-driven-development-screencast-number-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/6XMoZ7snuKo?list=PLbNxoJawcer22UE8lT93-fX8ZYFNtoXFu" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Recommended to watch in a full-screen and on 720p or higher quality.</p>

<p>List of all TDD Screencasts can be <a href="/blog/categories/tdd-screencasts/">found here</a>.</p>

<h2>Script</h2>

<p>Hello, hello! I am Oleksii Fedorov, and this is the second episode of
Test-Driven-Development Screencast.</p>

<p>Now that I think about it, first episode was more of an audio podcast (with two
and half visual slides), rather than a screencast. Don&rsquo;t worry - this episode
will be full of code and actual action time on the screen.</p>

<p>Today we are going to implement a sorting algorithm. We will not come up with
algorithm beforehand and we will simply let it emerge by itself, while we are
doing TDD.</p>

<p>Lets jump in!</p>

<pre><code>./watch.sh  # So I have here small script, that will watch changes in my code
            # and will run all my tests. Additionally, it will show me the
            # result in the notification bar (you will see, shortly).

vim         # 1) Create test file
            # 2) Follow TDD rules to the letter
</code></pre>

<p>I think we are done here. And notice, that this is a bubble sort algorithm. Now
lets ask a question, why the worst possible algorithm have emerged, while we
were using TDD. That is an interesting question.</p>

<p>But first, lets ask ourselves a question: Are we kind to the user of our
function? The answer is - NO. We are mutating the argument, that user passed to
us. And this mutation might be unexpected. At least our test suite doesn&rsquo;t even
mention such behavior.</p>

<p>The root of the problem is this little swap operation that we have here:</p>

<pre><code># show swap operation on the screen
a[0], a[1] = {a[1], a[0]}
</code></pre>

<p>I wonder, what will happen if we were to ban swap operation (and any kind of
mutation of the argument of the function), and implement sorting algorithm
again?</p>

<p>Find out next time, on the next episode of Test-Driven-Development! Have a good
day.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
