<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Javascript | That TDD Fellow | Tech Blog | Screencasts]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-12-28T20:49:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oleksii Fedorov (waterlink)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Test-Driven Development With Javascript: End-to-End Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/12/23/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-end-to-end-testing/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-23T10:13:33+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/12/23/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-end-to-end-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Level: Beginner.</strong></p>

<p>&ldquo;Learning TDD with Javascript&rdquo; is the series of articles where we learn basics of automated testing and test-driven development. While the language of choice for the code examples is Javascript, all described concepts are language-agnostic and are applicable in various technological stacks. In these articles, a reader is expected to do small exercises after each major topic to reinforce that theoretical knowledge with practice. Some of these exercises are practical and will involve coding, or simple writing; others will be food for thought. Also, a reader might want to get their feedback on these exercises, so don&rsquo;t hesitate to send the results my way: <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#111;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x6b;&#x73;&#105;&#105;&#x40;&#x74;&#100;&#x64;&#x66;&#101;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#111;&#119;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#109;">&#111;&#108;&#x65;&#107;&#115;&#105;&#x69;&#64;&#x74;&#x64;&#100;&#102;&#x65;&#x6c;&#108;&#x6f;&#x77;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;</a> - feedback on the practice is quite important as it helps to improve quicker, when you know what is well and what can be improved and how. Also, don&rsquo;t hesitate to send any questions and feedback regarding the content of these articles. Your questions, feedback, and your practical results will help authors shape this content better.</p>

<p>Today we are going to learn how to write tests that imitate real user interaction for the whole application. We are going to build a small web application using Vanilla Javascript. Vanilla Javascript is a plain Javascript without any framework or library. Such tests that imitate real user interaction via User Interface (UI) are called End-to-End Tests. These tests are the most simple to write because we only need to think about our application in the same way user does:</p>

<ul>
<li>Imitating the user clicking on the button would mean for us to trigger a button click;</li>
<li>Imitating the user typing text in the input field would mean for us to change input&rsquo;s value;</li>
<li>Imitating the user clicking on the link would mean for us to trigger a link click;</li>
<li>And so on.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>We don&rsquo;t need to think about specific implementation details, such as: which functions and classes do we have in our code and how they interact with each other, is there any interaction with the back-end server or 3rd-party API. Also, we don&rsquo;t need to be proficient with interaction testing - this is the topic for the future series.</p>

<p>Of course, for that kind of simplicity we are trading something off. In the case of End-to-End tests, they are slower, suffer concurrency, wait, and timeout problems, and are harder to maintain in the long run. We don&rsquo;t have to worry about that just yet because we want to learn how to write tests in general, and this kind of simplicity is perfect for us in this case.</p>

<p>Such simplicity stems from the fact that End-to-End tests, mostly, are direct translations of user stories (use case scenarios) into the UI manipulation code.</p>

<h2>User Story</h2>

<p>User stories are scenarios describing an individual feature of the software via user story context, sequences of user interactions and user expectations. User story context is the description of the situation the user and the software system are in at the beginning of the scenario. An example of the system context: &ldquo;user John is registered in the system with password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo;.&rdquo; An example of the user context: &ldquo;user is at the login page.&rdquo; User interaction is the description of a particular action user takes inside of the system, usually, doing something within the UI, for example: &ldquo;User enters email &lsquo;<a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#x6a;&#111;&#104;&#110;&#64;&#101;&#120;&#97;&#109;&#x70;&#108;&#101;&#46;&#111;&#114;&#x67;">&#x6a;&#111;&#x68;&#110;&#x40;&#x65;&#x78;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#108;&#x65;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#103;</a>&rsquo; in the email input field&rdquo; or &ldquo;User clicks on the submit button.&rdquo; Finally, user expectation is the description of what particular information user should receive from the system, for example: &ldquo;User sees the success message on the page&rdquo; or &ldquo;User receives the email with the verification code.&rdquo;</p>

<p>User stories come in different flavor and formats. It can be a free-form text, describing three parts: context, interactions, and expectations; or it can be in a formal &ldquo;Given-When-Then&rdquo; form. &ldquo;Given&rdquo; part is the sequence of the user story context descriptions, &ldquo;When&rdquo; part is the sequence of the user interaction descriptions, and &ldquo;Then&rdquo; part is the sequence of user expectation descriptions. Both forms can be used interchangeably, and some software companies use one or another formal version of the user story format consistently.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example of the free-form user story together with the example of the Given-When-Then user story for the same feature:</p>

<div class="next-table-layout-is-fixed"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Free-form</th>
<th>Given-When-Then</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User with email &lsquo;<a href="&#109;&#x61;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#106;&#x6f;&#104;&#110;&#64;&#101;&#120;&#x61;&#109;&#x70;&#108;&#101;&#46;&#111;&#114;&#103;">&#x6a;&#x6f;&#104;&#110;&#64;&#x65;&#x78;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#x6c;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;</a>&rsquo; and password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; exists in the system<br>John enters his email &lsquo;<a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#111;&#x68;&#x6e;&#64;&#x65;&#x78;&#x61;&#109;&#112;&#x6c;&#x65;&#46;&#111;&#114;&#103;">&#106;&#x6f;&#x68;&#110;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#109;&#112;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;</a>&rsquo; into the email field and his password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; into the password field on the login page<br>After that John submits the login form<br>Finally, John expects to see their profile page with the indication of him being logged in (name &lsquo;John&rsquo; is present on the page)</td>
<td><strong>Given</strong> User with email &lsquo;<a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#106;&#x6f;&#x68;&#x6e;&#x40;&#x65;&#x78;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#x6c;&#101;&#x2e;&#111;&#114;&#x67;">&#106;&#x6f;&#104;&#x6e;&#64;&#101;&#x78;&#x61;&#109;&#x70;&#108;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;</a>&rsquo; and password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; exists<br><strong>And</strong> I am at the login page<br><strong>When</strong> I enter &lsquo;<a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#106;&#111;&#104;&#110;&#x40;&#101;&#x78;&#x61;&#x6d;&#112;&#x6c;&#101;&#46;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;">&#106;&#x6f;&#x68;&#x6e;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#x61;&#109;&#x70;&#x6c;&#101;&#46;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;</a>&rsquo; in the email field<br><strong>And</strong> I enter &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; in the password field<br><strong>And</strong> I click on the submit button<br><strong>Then</strong> I see the profile page<br><strong>And</strong> I see my name as the title of the profile page</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>As we can see, free-form can be very vague and is very flexible, and formal form is more strict and precise. The free-form on its own doesn&rsquo;t have much upsides or downsides - it is as good as it is written. On the other hand, the formal form does give us some value and also trades something off for that value. They are generally easy to write and, because they are so specific, are easy to translate to the automated test. On the other hand, they may hamper creativity either while creating the user story or when implementing it.</p>

<p>It is important to mention that these use case scenarios are not full user stories or features. One feature can have multiple scenarios like that - together they are called acceptance criteria. When all such scenarios of the given feature work correctly, the feature is done. There is another vital part of the user story - general description, that should contain the rationale behind the story and the value for the user or any other important actor in the system, such as the stakeholder. Before we write scenarios, we often come up with the rationale like that and it drives us to write a scenario. For example, for the feature above we would have used something like that:</p>

<div class="next-table-layout-is-fixed"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Free-form</th>
<th>Given-When-Then</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>John needs to authenticate to the system so that he can access his private content</td>
<td><strong>As John</strong>, I want to be able to authenticate to the system<br><strong>So that</strong> I can access my private content</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Because formal form user stories are more precise, easier to write and simpler to translate to the automated test, we are going to use them to learn End-to-End testing in the context of Test-Driven Development.</p>

<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write a scenario for authentication story, when John enters the wrong password.</li>
<li>Write a user story with rationale and scenarios for the sign-up feature.</li>
<li>Imagine we are developing an instant messaging application. What do you think would be the next feature after login/sign-up? Write the user story with rationale and scenarios for this feature.</li>
</ol>


<p>Do you have questions? Or do you want to get quick feedback on how you did the exercises? - mail me: <a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#111;&#108;&#x65;&#x6b;&#115;&#x69;&#105;&#64;&#x74;&#x64;&#x64;&#x66;&#x65;&#108;&#x6c;&#111;&#119;&#46;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#111;&#108;&#101;&#x6b;&#x73;&#x69;&#x69;&#64;&#116;&#x64;&#x64;&#102;&#101;&#108;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#119;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#109;</a></p>

<h2>Setting Up the Project</h2>

<p>Now we will be writing a simple web application, using Vanilla Javascript (ECMAScript 5), so that our setup is rather simple. For the testing, we will be using a standalone version of the Jasmine testing framework. Also, we will be writing a single page application (SPA), so that we don&rsquo;t have to worry about rendering different pages in our tests for now. We are aiming for the following directory structure of our project:</p>

<pre><code>.
├── lib
├───── .. external libraries, such as Jasmine ..
├── spec
├───── .. sources with Jasmine automated tests ..
└── src
├───── .. sources with our main code ..
├── index.html       - entry point to the application
├── SpecRunner.html  - entry point to our test suite
</code></pre>

<p>First, create required directories: <code>lib</code>, <code>spec</code> and <code>src</code>. Then download the latest standalone Jasmine release here: <a href="https://github.com/jasmine/jasmine/releases">https://github.com/jasmine/jasmine/releases</a> (jasmine-standalone-{version}.zip file). At the time of writing, the version is <code>2.5.2</code>. Unzip that file into your project directory. You should get the following files from it:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>./lib/jasmine-2.5.2/</code> directory - contains all the resources required by Jasmine.</li>
<li><code>./SpecRunner.html</code> - example entry point to our test suite.</li>
<li><code>./src/Player.js</code> and <code>./src/Song.js</code> - example source files.</li>
<li><code>./spec/PlayerSpec.js</code> and <code>./spec/SpecHelper.js</code> - example automated Jasmine tests.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, try to open <code>SpecRunner.html</code> in your browser. It should run these example tests, and they should all pass. Here is how it should look like:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-example-run.png" alt="Jasmine example test run with all tests green" /></p>

<p>Also, create an empty <code>index.html</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html lang="en"&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Title&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>And now we should have the desired project structure. So how does that Jasmine testing framework works, anyways?</p>

<h2>Crash Course into Jasmine</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example test file to get the gist of how Jasmine works:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/PlayerSpec.js

describe("Player", function() {
  var player;
  var song;

  beforeEach(function() {
    player = new Player();
    song = new Song();
  });

  it("should be able to play a Song", function() {
    player.play(song);
    expect(player.currentlyPlayingSong).toEqual(song);

    //demonstrates use of custom matcher
    expect(player).toBePlaying(song);
  });

  describe("when song has been paused", function() {
    beforeEach(function() {
      player.play(song);
      player.pause();
    });

    it("should indicate that the song is currently paused", function() {
      expect(player.isPlaying).toBeFalsy();

      // demonstrates use of 'not' with a custom matcher
      expect(player).not.toBePlaying(song);
    });

    it("should be possible to resume", function() {
      player.resume();
      expect(player.isPlaying).toBeTruthy();
      expect(player.currentlyPlayingSong).toEqual(song);
    });
  });

  // demonstrates use of spies to intercept and test method calls
  it("tells the current song if the user has made it a favorite", function() {
    spyOn(song, 'persistFavoriteStatus');

    player.play(song);
    player.makeFavorite();

    expect(song.persistFavoriteStatus).toHaveBeenCalledWith(true);
  });

  //demonstrates use of expected exceptions
  describe("#resume", function() {
    it("should throw an exception if song is already playing", function() {
      player.play(song);

      expect(function() {
        player.resume();
      }).toThrowError("song is already playing");
    });
  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>First important concept here is the <code>describe("...", function () { ... })</code>. <code>describe</code> function is used to describe a certain concept or a certain context. For example, <code>describe("Player", ...)</code> means that we are going to define tests for <code>Player</code> class or some other <code>Player</code> concept. Also, describes can be nested to indicate that we are describing some specific context (<code>describe("when a song has been paused", ...)</code>) or sub-concept of current concept, such as the method of currently described class (<code>describe("#resume", ...)</code>). That is a good example, of what the unit test suite might be describing. In the case of End-to-End tests we would like to describe a full feature, so <code>describe("Login Feature", ...)</code> is a good bet. The second argument for the <code>describe</code> is the function that will contain all tests and sub-describes for the described concept. This function is the capturing closure, so defining variables and functions on the outer-level describe will make them available on the inner-level describes and the tests themselves.</p>

<p>Second important concept here is the <code>it("...", function () { ... })</code>. <code>it</code> function is used to create a test for the currently described concept, context or sub-concept. The first argument is the description of what <em>it</em> does, where <em>it</em> is the described concept. For example, given we describe a <code>music player</code> and our context is <code>when the volume is at max</code>, then we might write the test <code>it("is deafening", ...)</code>. In the case of End-to-End tests we are describing a feature, so <em>it</em> will refer to our application, or application&rsquo;s user interface, for example: <code>it("shows user's nickname", ...)</code>. The second argument to the <code>it</code> is the function with the test itself. Here we will setup the stage for the test, call our main code and verify that everything happened as we expect.</p>

<p>Finally, the third important concept is the <code>expect(...).to...</code>. That is Jasmine&rsquo;s form of assertion. That is where we verify that our code worked as we expect it to. As an argument to expect we provide an actual value. The actual value is something that our code has returned as a result of the function or method execution or something that we have read from the UI using UI manipulation code, or something that we have read from some 3rd party service, such as our back-end server, 3rd-party API or database. Essentially, this is the value that we are verifying to be correct. The second part is the Jasmine matcher - the method defined on the object, that is returned from <code>expect(value)</code> call, that allows us to define what we want to assert about that value. The most used one is <code>toEqual(...)</code>, which asserts that the value was equal to some expected value.</p>

<p>These three concepts should be enough to start writing tests. Don&rsquo;t worry about everything else that you see in this example file from standalone Jasmine distribution. We will discover some of these concepts as we go. Now, let&rsquo;s remove <code>src/Player.js</code>, <code>src/Song.js</code>, <code>spec/PlayerSpec.js</code> and <code>spec/SpecHelper.js</code>, and run our test suite - it is enough to reload the page to re-run our test suite. Test run should report that <code>No specs found</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-no-specs-found.png" alt="Jasmine no specs found example" /></p>

<p>To get the gist of how <code>describe("...", function () { ... })</code>, <code>it("...", function () { ... })</code> and <code>expect(...).toEqual(...)</code> works, let&rsquo;s write our first failing test. Also, that will let us see if the testing framework is configured correctly and is capable of showing us the test failure. Let&rsquo;s create a new file called <code>spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js

describe("testing framework", function () {
  it("works", function () {
    expect(2 + 2).toEqual(5);
  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>And we need to add this test file to the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>:</p>

<p>&#8220;`html</p>

<!-- include source files here... -->




<!-- include spec files here... -->


<script src="spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js"></script>


<pre><code>
And if we run our test suite, we should see a failure:
</code></pre>

<p>testing framework works
  Expected 4 to equal 5.
&#8220;`</p>

<p>And we ought to make it pass by fixing our incorrect assertion: <code>expect(2 + 2).toEqual(4);</code>. And if we run the test suite again, by reloading the page in the browser, all the test should pass.</p>

<h2>Writing our First Simple Tests</h2>

<p>Now we can write some real tests to practice usage of <code>describe</code>, <code>it</code> and <code>expect(...).toEqual</code>: let&rsquo;s create <code>ArithmeticsSpec.js</code> and write some tests for behavior of <code>add</code> function:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js

describe("Arithmetics", function () {

  describe("#add(a, b)", function () {
    it("calculates the sum of two numbers", function () {
      // ARRANGE
      var a = 3;
      var b = 4;
      var expected = 7;

      // ACT
      var actual = Arithmetics.add(a, b);

      // ASSERT
      expect(actual).toEqual(expected);
    });
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to add the <code>&lt;script src="spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</code> to the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. This test will fail first because <code>Arithmetics</code> module is not defined. We will define it as an empty object. Next failure is because <code>Arithmetics.add</code> is not a function - it is undefined. We will define that function with two arguments inside of the <code>Arithmetics</code> object. Finally, the test will fail, because we expect the result to be seven, but it was undefined. We will make the simplest thing we can do to pass the failing test - return seven. That will make the test pass. The code will be in <code>src/Arithmetics.js</code>, which we include in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>, and will look like that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/Arithmetics.js

var Arithmetics = {
  add: function (a, b) {
    return 7;
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>That, of course, is not correct implementation, so we need another test to drive out the proper implementation - test with different inputs and a different result. To make it pass we will have to use <code>a + b</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js
describe("Arithmetics", function () {

  describe("#add(a, b)", function () {
    it("calculates the sum of two numbers", function () { ... });

    it("calculates the sum of two other numbers", function () {
      // ARRANGE
      var a = 73;
      var b = 89;
      var expected = 162;

      // ACT
      var actual = Arithmetics.add(a, b);

      // ASSERT
      expect(actual).toEqual(expected);
    });
  });

});

// src/Arithmetics.js
var Arithmetics = {
  add: function (a, b) {
    return a + b;
  }
};
</code></pre>

<h3>Three &ldquo;A&#8221;s: Arrange, Act, and Assert</h3>

<p>Have you noticed three comments that I have left in the example tests&#8217; code: <code>ARRANGE</code>, <code>ACT</code> and <code>ASSERT</code>? These are three &ldquo;A&#8221;s of writing a good test. Arrange is the part of the test, where we set up the stage: prepare input data, create objects, load resources, change the state of the system - it is the part where we create the context for our test. Act is the part of the test, where we call our system under the test. In the <code>Arithmetics</code> example it was a function <code>Arithmetics.add(a, b)</code>. The system under the test can return some useful value or change its state. To verify that either is correct we, finally, use Assert section of our test - part of the test where we verify the outcome of the call to the system under the test.</p>

<p>The sections <code>ARRANGE</code>, <code>ACT</code> and <code>ASSERT</code> are spelled out in the comments only for the reader&rsquo;s convenience - usually, real projects don&rsquo;t have such comments. It is worth noting that for learning and practicing purposes it is a good idea to name these sections explicitly in our tests - this develops a habit of recognizing which part of the test should belong to which section. Also, the formula Act -> Arrange -> Assert makes it easier to come up with the test when we lack deep experience in testing, or with the particular testing framework, or an environment.</p>

<p>Going a bit back to our user story scenarios: have you noticed the connection between &ldquo;Arrange, Act and Assert&rdquo; and &ldquo;Given-When-Then&rdquo;? Arrange part of the test corresponds to the Given part of the scenario, Act part of the test corresponds to the When part of the scenario, and Assert part of the test corresponds to the Then part of the scenario. Let&rsquo;s see it on of our previous example scenarios:</p>

<div class="next-table-is-top-aligned"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Test Section</th>
<th>Scenario Step</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARRANGE</td>
<td><strong>Given</strong> User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists<br><strong>And</strong> I am at the login page</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><br></td>
<td><br></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACT</td>
<td><strong>When</strong> I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field<br><strong>And</strong> I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field<br><strong>And</strong> I click on the submit button</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><br></td>
<td><br></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ASSERT</td>
<td><strong>Then</strong> I see the profile page<br><strong>And</strong> I see my name as the title of the profile page</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write tests and implement functions on <code>Arithmetics</code> module: <code>subtract</code>, <code>multiply</code> and <code>divide</code>.</li>
<li>Inline Arrange, Act and Assert in a one-liner. Can you still recognize implicit Arrange, Act and Assert sections in that one line? Is it more or less readable? Is there a middle ground between two versions? Why would you choose one or the other?</li>
<li>Classify parts of the free-form story for the user log in from before as Arrange, Act, and Assert. Was it easier, than classifying formal Given-When-Then form? Was it harder? Or maybe the same? How would it be if you never saw Given-When-Then version of that free-form story?</li>
</ol>


<h2>Writing our First End-to-End Test</h2>

<p>Now that we know approximately, how to arrange the steps of our scenario into the test, let&rsquo;s give it a shot. We will start by creating a new test file for our login feature called <code>LoginFeatureSpec.js</code>. Don&rsquo;t forget to put an appropriate script tag in the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. We will start by writing the skeleton of our test suite: <code>describe</code> and <code>it</code> inside of it. Next, we will put scenario steps as comments to our test, and we will split them into three sections: Arrange, Act, and Assert. It will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js

describe("Login Feature", function () {

  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE
    // Given User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists
    // And I am at the login page

    // ACT
    // When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field
    // And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field
    // And I click on the submit button

    // ASSERT
    // Then I see the profile page
    // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>Next step would be to change the first <strong>Given</strong> comment to the function call. We should give a good readable name to that function. One straightforward option would be <code>givenUserExists(email, password).' Another good option is</code>addUser({email: email, password: password})<code>. While they are not that different, I prefer</code>addUser<code>for its higher conceptual flexibility - we will likely need that function in some different scenario step in the future. While I prefer that, we should not do that yet, because we might never need the function like that, and</code>givenUserExists<code>will do us more good right now since it resembles the scenario step so much. When we need this flexibility, we'll perform a refactoring. So for now, let's create an empty function with that name in a new file</code>spec/FeatureSteps.js<code>and load this file from our</code>SpecRunner.html`.</p>

<p>This empty function, on its own, doesn&rsquo;t do us much good because all our tests will pass. If we continue replacing our steps in comments with such functions, we will end up with one big failure at the Assert section, and we will have to write a lot of code at once to fix that. To drive ourselves to implement the function <code>givenUserExists</code> properly right now, we should write an assertion right after the call. This assertion is not part of Assert section - it is a part of test-driving the functionality of our feature steps. A good assertion here will be to ask our user storage mechanism if such user exists right after we created that user. Also, it would be a good idea to check that user does not exist, before we created it. Also, we will extract variables <code>email</code> and <code>password</code> because we have to repeat them all over the place already. Let&rsquo;s see how it will look like:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js

describe("Login Feature", function () {

  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE

    // Given User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists
    var email = "john@example.org";
    var password = "welcome";
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);
    givenUserExists(email, password);
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);

    // ...
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>When we run our tests, the breadcrumbs of test failures will drive us to create this basic functionality. First, we will create <code>Users.js</code> with empty <code>Users</code> module and import it from <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. Then, next failure will drive us to add method <code>exists(email, password)</code> on <code>Users</code> module, that will always return <code>false</code>. Next, make function <code>givenUserExists(email, password)</code> call <code>Users.add(email, password)</code>, which in turn will make us create a function <code>Users.add(email, password)</code>, that will store email-password pair to the list of users in the memory. And, finally, make <code>Users.exists</code> to search for the email-password pair in that in-memory list. And finally, our test will pass. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how these steps will look in our code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// =&gt; Error: Users is undefined
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {};

// =&gt; Error: Users.exists is not a function
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  exists: function (email, password) {}
};

// =&gt; Error: expected undefined to equal false
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  exists: function (email, password) {
    return false;
  }
};

// =&gt; Error: expected false to equal true
// in the (second assertion)
// in spec/FeatureSteps.js:
function givenUserExists(email, password) {
  Users.add(email, password);
}

// =&gt; Error: Users.add is not a function
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  users: [],

  exists: function (email, password) { ... },

  add: function (email, password) {
    this.users.push({email: email, password: password});
  }
}

// this still fails with:
// =&gt; Error: expected false to equal true
// because we need to implement Users.exists "properly"
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  users: [],

  exists: function (email, password) {
    return this.users.length &gt; 0;
  },

  add: function (email, password) { ... }
}

// =&gt; All tests PASS
</code></pre>

<p>It is funny, how simple <code>Users.exists(email, password)</code> function is. It verifies that we have at least one user. While this is not a correct code, this is good enough for our current test. As we know that this code is not entirely correct, we need to remember to write the test(s) to prove it incorrect, so that we can make it proper with confidence. Since we want first to finish the current test, we should add a to-do list item to write such test. We have two edge cases here that will not work with our implementation: when we have only one user in the system and the credentials we provided do not match and when we have multiple users in the system, and we provide correct credentials for the second one:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">xdescribe("when user has different credentials", function () {
  it("does not allow to login with wrong credentials", function () {

  });
});

xdescribe("when there are more than one user", function () {
  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {

  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>Have you noticed <code>xdescribe</code>? It is a different form of the <code>describe</code>, that allows us to mark the whole context as pending. It won&rsquo;t run the tests inside, and it will mark them as pending in the test run report. That is the ultimate way to maintain a Test-Driven TODO List. As we test-drive our code, we will find more of these. In the report they look like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-e2e-pending-tests.png" alt="pending jasmine tests" /></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s finish continue implementing our steps. The comment <code>And I am at the login page</code> transparently becomes a function <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code>. As we already have seen, it doesn&rsquo;t do us any good just to replace the comment with a function call that does nothing - so we should surround it with proper assertions. We know that login page should have some text input for email and another password field for password, and we will need a button to confirm user&rsquo;s intent to log in. Also, because we are developing a single page application, we would need some container for the currently active page. Let&rsquo;s say we need these things:</p>

<ul>
<li>Initially, we will have only one container with <code>id="page"</code> and no content. We probably ought to define it in our HTML file.</li>
<li>When we render our login page, we should have:

<ul>
<li>email text input field with <code>id="email"</code>,</li>
<li>password input field with <code>id="password"</code>,</li>
<li>and button with <code>id="do_login"</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Now that we have spelt this out, it is fairly straightforward to write assertions surrounding the <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code> call:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// Initially, we will have only one container with `id="page"`
var container = document.querySelector("#page");
expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
// and no content
expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");
</code></pre>

<p>That fails because we don&rsquo;t have such element in our HTML. We need to create it both in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. Also, now it will be important to move all our <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags from the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> to the <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> below the container that we have just created. <code>SpecRunner.html</code> should look this way after that:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="utf-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Jasmine Spec Runner v2.5.2&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/png" href="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine_favicon.png"&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine.css"&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

    &lt;div id="page"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine-html.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/boot.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;!-- include source files here... --&gt;
    &lt;script src="src/Arithmetics.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="src/Users.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;!-- include spec files here... --&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/FeatureSteps.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Now, our next failure is that <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code> function is not defined. We can define it as empty function in our <code>spec/FeatureSteps.js</code> file for now. This will turn our tests green again. We still haven&rsquo;t made our assertions about the state of the UI after the call to <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code> - let&rsquo;s do this now:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("input");
expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");
</code></pre>

<p>That fails with the error <code>Cannot read property tagName of null</code>, which means that we don&rsquo;t have <code>#email</code> element inside of the <code>#page</code> container. Simplest thing to do would be to add that element to the <code>#page</code> container in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. And it won&rsquo;t work! Because we have an assertion that verifies, that before calling to the <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code> we do not have anything in the <code>#page</code> container. Now we have to do something useful in the function <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code>. For example, we can call <code>LoginPage.render()</code>. Which does not exist yet and we will need to create it in the file <code>src/LoginPage.js</code> and load it from our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. To fix current failure we will need to create a <code>#email</code> element there and append it to our <code>#page</code> container:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
  LoginPage.render();
}

// src/LoginPage.js
var LoginPage = {
  render: function () {
    var emailInput = document.createElement("div");
    emailInput.id = "email";

    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    container.appendChild(emailInput);
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>That makes the current test failure go away, but we have two more: <code>Expected 'DIV' to equal 'input'.</code> and <code>Expected undefined to equal 'email'.</code>. To make these pass, we would need to change <code>document.createElement(...)</code> call to use <code>input</code> tag name and also we will need to set the input type to <code>email</code>. And as we see, the tag name stored in <code>emailInput.tagName</code> is all-caps, so we will have to fix our assertion also to expect that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// first we'll fix the assertion:
// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");

// and then we will fix the emailInput creation:
// in src/LoginPage.js
var emailInput = document.createElement("input");
emailInput.id = "email";
emailInput.type = "email";
</code></pre>

<p>And if we run our tests, they all pass. Great! We should now do the same for our password input field and the login button:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");
var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");

// in src/LoginPage.js
var passwordInput = document.createElement("input");
passwordInput.id = "password";
passwordInput.type = "password";
container.appendChild(passwordInput);

var loginButton = document.createElement("button");
loginButton.id = "do_login";
loginButton.textContent = "Login";
container.appendChild(loginButton);
</code></pre>

<p>And all tests pass again. Let&rsquo;s take another look at how our test looks like. It is quite complicated, and it has so much stuff, that is hugely detailed and precise, that it is not possible to see a user story scenario there anymore. One possible solution to that problem is to push the assertions that are related to the feature scenario step to the respective step functions. Now it looks much better. We should use the same concept for all our further steps. After refactoring test code looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
  // ARRANGE
  var email = "john@example.org";
  var password = "welcome";
  givenUserExists(email, password);
  givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

  // ACT
  // When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field
  // And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field
  // And I click on the submit button

  // ASSERT
  // Then I see the profile page
  // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
});

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password) {
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

    Users.add(email, password);

    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);
}

function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");

    LoginPage.render();

    var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
    expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");

    var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
    expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");

    var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
    expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
    expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s follow the same pattern for our Act section. First, we will deal with <code>When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field</code>. This seems to be a call to a function <code>whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email)</code> - we will implement it using Javascript&rsquo;s APIs. We will do the same for the <code>And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field</code>, which will use the same function <code>whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password).</code> Finally, we will implement <code>whenIClickOn("#do_login")</code> as a replacement for the comment <code>And I click on the submit button</code>. We will also sprinkle assertions inside of the steps to make sure that we are using the Javascript APIs correctly. The code will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE
    var email = "john@example.org";
    var password = "welcome";
    givenUserExists(email, password);
    givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

    // ACT
    whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email);
    whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password);
    whenIClickOn("#do_login");

    // ASSERT
    // Then I see the profile page
    // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
});

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function whenIEnterInTheField(selector, value) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(element.value).toEqual("");

    element.value = value;

    var elementAfterChange = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.value).toEqual(value);
}

function whenIClickOn(selector) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);

    element.click();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now comes the most interesting part of writing this feature test - Assert section. So far, Arrange and Act sections were driving us to create an infrastructure-like code of our application. Now, with Assert section we will have to implement more of our domain logic. Let&rsquo;s start with the <code>Then I see the profile page</code>. Let&rsquo;s try to figure our what that could mean:</p>

<ul>
<li>We no longer have a login page in our <code>#page</code> container.</li>
<li><code>#page</code> container should somehow indicate that we are on the <code>Profile</code> page:

<ul>
<li>could be achieved by adding a sub-container with <code>id="profile_page"</code> to it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We don&rsquo;t know much more about what the profile page is. What we do know is:

<ul>
<li>the profile page has a name of the user as the title of the page.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Interesting, so far, we didn&rsquo;t have a concept of the Name of the User. I guess it is time to create one in our arrange block, with all the changes and additional assertions in our feature steps that we have to do:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
// ARRANGE
var email = "john@example.org";
var password = "welcome";
var name = "John Smith";
givenUserExists(email, password, name);

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password, name) {
  expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

  Users.add(email, password, name);            // &lt;=

  expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);

  expect(Users.nameOf(email)).toEqual(name);   // &lt;=
}

// also we need to add name field to the user data
// and implement nameOf(email) function
// in src/Users.js
add: function (email, password, name) {
  this.users.push({
    email: email,
    password: password,
    name: name
  });
},

nameOf: function (email) {
  return this.users[0].name;
}
</code></pre>

<p>And the tests will pass again. And now we have a tested concept of the name in our code. Tested - to the extent required for this test, where we have only one user in the system. Now we can replace the comment <code>Then I see the profile page</code> with the scenario step function call <code>thenISeeTheProfilePage()</code>. The implementation of it will verify that <code>#email</code>, <code>#password</code> and <code>#do_login</code> are no longer present on the page and it will verify that container <code>#page-profile</code> is present and it has <code>#title</code> element in it. Making it pass will require us to add a <code>click</code> event listener to the <code>loginButton</code> in the <code>LoginPage</code>, that will remove contents of the <code>#page</code> container and will call to <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> following the analogy of <code>LoginPage</code>. That drives us to create this module and its <code>render()</code> function. According to our next test failure, this function should create <code>#profile_page</code> sub-container in <code>#page</code> container, so we do that. Finally, we have one last failure, that drives us to create <code>#title</code> element in <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> function. And all tests are green again. Let&rsquo;s take a look at these changes:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
// ASSERT
// Then I see the profile page
thenISeeTheProfilePage();

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function thenISeeTheProfilePage() {
  // assert login page is gone
  expect(document.querySelector("#email")).toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#password")).toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#do_login")).toEqual(null);

  // assert profile page is present
  expect(document.querySelector("#page #profile_page")).not.toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#profile_page #title")).not.toEqual(null);
}

// in src/LoginPage.js at the end of render() function:
render: function() {
  // ...

  loginButton.addEventListener("click", LoginPage.onLogin);
},

onLogin: function () {
  container.innerHTML = "";
  ProfilePage.render();
}

// in src/ProfilePage.js
var ProfilePage = {
  render: function () {
    var profileContainer = document.createElement("div");
    profileContainer.id = "profile_page";
    container.appendChild(profileContainer);

    var title = document.createElement("h1");
    title.id = "title";
    profileContainer.appendChild(title);
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>At last, we can implement the last step - <code>And I see my name as the title of the profile page</code>. A good guess for the step name would be <code>thenISeeTextAt("#title", name)</code>. The function will simply select element <code>#title</code> and verify its <code>element.textContent</code>. As expected, it fails with the error <code>Expected '' to equal 'John Smith'</code> and we should fix that within the <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> function by assigning <code>title.textContent</code> to the <code>Users.currentUser().name</code>. This fails because we didn&rsquo;t define <code>Users.currentUser()</code> function and this is simple to do for our current test - just return the first user. After that all our tests pass. The code will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
thenISeeTextAt("#title", name);

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function thenISeeTextAt(selector, text) {
  var element = document.querySelector(selector);
  expect(element.textContent).toEqual(text);
}

// in src/ProfilePage.js
title.textContent = Users.currentUser().name;

// in src/Users.js
currentUser: function () {
    return this.users[0];
}
</code></pre>

<p>We have finally, implemented our first feature test. That was quite some work. Also, the functionality of <code>Users</code> module is way incomplete - we need to write more tests to cover different cases. That is how our test code and production code looks like:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
describe("Login Feature", function () {

    it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
        // ARRANGE
        var email = "john@example.org";
        var password = "welcome";
        var name = "John Smith";
        givenUserExists(email, password, name);
        givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

        // ACT
        whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email);
        whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password);
        whenIClickOn("#do_login");

        // ASSERT
        thenISeeTheProfilePage();
        thenISeeTextAt("#title", name);
    });

    xdescribe("when user has different credentials", function () {
        it("does not allow to login with wrong credentials", function () {

        });
    });

    xdescribe("when there are more than one user", function () {
        it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {

        });
    });

});
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password, name) {
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

    Users.add(email, password, name);

    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);
    expect(Users.nameOf(email)).toEqual(name);
}

function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");

    LoginPage.render();

    var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
    expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");

    var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
    expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");

    var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
    expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
    expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");
}

function whenIEnterInTheField(selector, value) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(element.value).toEqual("");

    element.value = value;

    var elementAfterChange = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.value).toEqual(value);
}

function whenIClickOn(selector) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);

    element.click();
}

function thenISeeTheProfilePage() {
    // assert login page is gone
    expect(document.querySelector("#email")).toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#password")).toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#do_login")).toEqual(null);

    // assert profile page is present
    expect(document.querySelector("#page #profile_page")).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#profile_page #title")).not.toEqual(null);
}

function thenISeeTextAt(selector, text) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.textContent).toEqual(text);
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/Users.js
var Users = {
    users: [],

    exists: function (email, password) {
        return this.users.length &gt; 0;
    },

    add: function (email, password, name) {
        this.users.push({
            email: email,
            password: password,
            name: name
        });
    },

    nameOf: function (email) {
        return this.users[0].name;
    },

    currentUser: function () {
        return this.users[0];
    }
};
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/LoginPage.js
var container = document.querySelector("#page");

var LoginPage = {
    render: function () {
        var emailInput = document.createElement("input");
        emailInput.id = "email";
        emailInput.type = "email";
        container.appendChild(emailInput);

        var passwordInput = document.createElement("input");
        passwordInput.id = "password";
        passwordInput.type = "password";
        container.appendChild(passwordInput);

        var loginButton = document.createElement("button");
        loginButton.id = "do_login";
        loginButton.textContent = "Login";
        container.appendChild(loginButton);

        loginButton.addEventListener("click", LoginPage.onLogin);
    },

    onLogin: function () {
        container.innerHTML = "";
        ProfilePage.render();
    }
};
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/ProfilePage.js
var ProfilePage = {
    render: function () {
        var profileContainer = document.createElement("div");
        profileContainer.id = "profile_page";
        container.appendChild(profileContainer);

        var title = document.createElement("h1");
        title.id = "title";
        title.textContent = Users.currentUser().name;
        profileContainer.appendChild(title);
    }
};
</code></pre>

<p>Now we could add <code>&lt;div id="page"&gt;</code> to our <code>index.html</code>, and load our <code>src/*</code> scripts after it, and add <code>&lt;script&gt;Users.add("john@example.org", "welcome", "John Smith"); LoginPage.render();&lt;/script&gt;</code> at the end to start our application. Enjoy the application that implements one happy path of our feature (we still have quite a few different paths to cover). Also, it might be a good idea to style the application slightly better, than plain inputs and buttons, but we are not going to cover that in these series. This single feature test takes a lot of time to write because it is the first feature test in the empty application. Essentially, it has driven a lot of different architectural decisions, which don&rsquo;t necessary need to be done the way they were done in this article. Writing a second test for the same feature is much easier and third one, and all consecutive are also easier.</p>

<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Remove <code>x</code> prefix from the <code>xdescribe</code> tests and implement them using techniques described in this article - write a user story scenario, translate it to the test code and make sure to fix all the test failures one feature step at a time.</li>
<li>Discover more interesting edge cases. Make the tests for them and make them all pass.</li>
<li>Write sign-up feature&rsquo;s user story and implement it with feature tests.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Today we have learned how to write tests for the whole application that imitate real user interaction. We have seen how, test-driving the functionality can help discovering new user story scenarios. Essentially, every time we write simple, but not so correct code that makes our test pass, we need to think what would be the scenario to prove that code wrong and add that scenario on our to-do list, which is represented by pending tests, which have only their descriptions.</p>

<p>In the next article of the series, we will dig deeper on what exactly we did today, what it means to Test-Drive the code, what are the laws, rules, tips and tricks of Test-Driven Development. Next article of the series assumes, that login and sign-up features are fully test-driven and implemented. We will be implementing a brand new feature of our application.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Your Own Testing Framework. Part 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/11/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-5/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-13T12:50:51+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/11/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the new issue of &ldquo;Build Your Own Testing Framework&rdquo; series! Did you notice, that out testing framework quits on the first failure? It probably should run all tests, collect all failures and present them nicely. This is what we are going to accomplish today:</p>

<ul>
<li>Make sure all tests run even when there is a failure.</li>
<li>Make sure exit code is correct.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>This article is the fifth one of the series “Build Your Own Testing Framework” so make sure to stick around for next parts! Find all posts of these series can <a href="/blog/categories/build-your-own-testing-framework/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Shall we get started?</p>

<h2>Catch and report a test failure</h2>

<p>Our test suite should no longer bubble up any exceptions. We can achieve that by making an appropriate assertion. And also we should verify that other tests execute after the failure:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function FailureTest(t) {
    this.testItDoesNotBubbleUpExceptions = function () {
        var aSpy = t.spy();

        t.assertNotThrow(function () {
            runTestSuite(function (t) {
                this.testFailure = function () {
                    t.assertTrue(false);
                };

                this.testSomething = aSpy;
            });
        });

        aSpy.assertCalled();
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>As expected, this fails with an appropriate error <code>Error: Expected not to throw error, but thrown 'Expected to be true, but got false'</code> indicating that we are bubbling up all errors at the moment. Also, notice how the execution of the whole test suite stops at that point, and it just exits the program with error code <code>1</code>. A simple <code>try .. catch</code> block will fix the issue:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in runTestSuite function
    for (var testName in testSuitePrototype) {
        if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
            reporter.reportTest(testName);
            var testSuite = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

            try {
                testSuite[testName]();
            } catch (error) {
                // do nothing, for now
            }
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>All tests now run successfully. This code is starting to become unreadable, so it is a good point to refactor. We will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Extract whole <code>try .. catch</code> as a function <code>runTest</code>. Its current responsibility is only to run the test and ignore any failure;</li>
<li>Extract contents of <code>if</code> statement that matches the test name as a function <code>handleTest</code>. Its responsibility is to report the test, create a fresh testSuite and kick off <code>runTest</code>;</li>
<li>Extract the whole <code>for</code> statement as <code>runAllTests</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is the final snippet of code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
    try {
        testSuite[testName]();
    } catch (error) {
        // do nothing, for now
    }
}

function handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor) {
    reporter.reportTest(testName);
    runTest(createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor), testName);
}

function runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor) {
    for (var testName in testSuitePrototype) {
        if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
            handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor);
        }
    }
}

function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    options = options || {};
    var reporter = options.reporter || new SimpleReporter();

    var testSuitePrototype = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

    reporter.reportTestSuite(
        getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
    );

    runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor);
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Exit with code 1</h2>

<p>Now, when at least one test fails in a suite of tests, the whole suite should fail (after running the rest of its tests). And the indicator of such failure should be an exit code of the process. Let&rsquo;s write a test:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function FailureTest(t) {
    // ...

    this.testItExitsWithProcessCodeOne = function () {
        var processSpy = new ProcessSpy();

        runTestSuite(function (t) {
            this.testFailure = function () {
                t.assertTrue(false);
            };
        }, {process: processSpy});

        t.assertEqual(1, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>As you might guess, we will need another object. It will be responsible for interaction with our process, i.e.: something that we can ask to &ldquo;exit with code 1.&rdquo; Because we can not ask our process to exit within the test run, we will have to create a spy. And we shall test-drive its functionality. There is something interesting that we should worry about before that - our test suite is passing currently.. but it shouldn&rsquo;t be!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s step back and think what just happened: clearly, we are writing the test, that can not possibly pass because we do not have <code>ProcessSpy</code> yet. So we are expecting a failure - we are expecting a thrown exception. That expectation is an important part of test-driven development: at all times we expect a very specific failure or we expect our tests to pass; if we do not receive a failure when expected and receive an unexpected failure, we should stop right there and think which part of our thinking and our assumptions is incorrect.</p>

<p><div class="v2-subscribe--inline">
  
  
  
  
  
  


<div class="mc_embed_signup">
  <form action="//tddfellow.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34&amp;id=6b61a409a5" method="post" class="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <div class="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
      <h3>Would You Like to Watch a Screencast with Me Implementing This?</h3>
      <div class="mc-field-group">
        <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
        <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true"><input type="text" name="b_535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34_6b61a409a5" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
        <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email mce-EMAIL" placeholder="Enter your email">
        <input type="submit" value="Claim video" name="subscribe" class="button mc-embedded-subscribe">
      </div>
      <div class="">
        <em>(we respect your privacy, unsubscribe at any time)</em>
      </div>
    </div>
  </form>
</div>

</div>
</p>

<p>Right now, tests do not fail, because we are ignoring all exceptions in our <code>try .. catch</code> that we introduced a couple of minutes ago. If we want to see failures again, let&rsquo;s modify <code>catch</code> block to just log all errors it receives:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
    try {
        testSuite[testName]();
    } catch (error) {
        console.log(error);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now our test suite outputs an expected error: <code>ReferenceError: ProcessSpy is not defined</code>. Also, it outputs some other failures that happen in our nested <code>runTestSuite</code> calls - we should fix them by providing <code>silenceFailures</code> option for nested <code>runTestSuite</code> call. We can focus now on the <code>ProcessSpy</code> failure and test-drive it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function ProcessSpy_BehaviorTest(t) {
    var processSpy = new ProcessSpy();
});
// =&gt; ReferenceError: ProcessSpy is not defined

function ProcessSpy() {}
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_initiallyIsNull = function () {
        t.assertEqual(null, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal null, but got: undefined

function ProcessSpy() {
    this.hasExitedWithCode = null;
}
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_isZero_afterExitZeroCall = function () {
        processSpy.exit(0);
        t.assertEqual(0, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; TypeError: processSpy.exit is not a function

// in ProcessSpy
    this.exit = function (code) {
        this.hasExitedWithCode = 0;
    };
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_isOne_afterExitOneCall = function () {
        processSpy.exit(1);
        t.assertEqual(1, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal 1, but got: 0

// in ProcessSpy
    this.exit = function (code) {
        this.hasExitedWithCode = code;
        // changed 0 to code      ^here^
    };
</code></pre>

<p>I think we have finished test-driving the functionality of <code>ProcessSpy</code>. It is time to get back to our failing test for a failure resulting in an exit with code 1. When we run this test suite, we are getting the following error message: <code>Error: Expected to equal 1, but got: null</code>.&lsquo; To pass this test, we will need to store the fact that we had a failure somewhere and at the end of the test suite run we can trigger exit with code 1 or 0, respectively. We could pass around a <code>status</code> object with boolean property <code>status.failed</code> and set it to <code>true</code> in our <code>catch</code> block:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    } catch (error) {
        if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
        status.failed = true;
    }
</code></pre>

<p>And at the end of <code>runTestSuite</code> function we could call <code>process.exit(1)</code> if <code>status.failed</code> was <code>true</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    // ...

    if (status.failed) {
        process.exit(1);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>While this works (as in &ldquo;tests pass after providing <code>fakeProcess</code> where needed for nested failing <code>runTestSuite</code> calls&rdquo;) state changes in this code are starting to be hard to follow and function signatures remind me of some horror movie:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
function runTest(testSuite, testName, silenceFailures, status)
function handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor, silenceFailures, status)
function runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor, silenceFailures, status)
</code></pre>

<p>These signatures smell like objects are hiding there in these functions. Let&rsquo;s find them!</p>

<h2>Quest for hidden objects</h2>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s extract the method object from the function <code>runTestSuite</code>. We will give it a name <code>TestSuiteRunContext</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    options = options || {};
    var reporter = options.reporter || new SimpleReporter();
    var process = options.process || global.process;
    var silenceFailures = options.silenceFailures || false;

    var status = {failed: false};

    var testSuitePrototype = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

    this.invoke = function () {
        reporter.reportTestSuite(
            getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
        );

        runAllTests(
            reporter,
            testSuitePrototype,
            testSuiteConstructor,
            silenceFailures,
            status
        );

        if (status.failed) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    };
}

function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    new TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options).invoke();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, if we were to move function <code>runAllTests</code> inside of this class, we would not need all these arguments (and all other functions we call):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    this.invoke = function () {
        reportTestSuite();
        runAllTests();
        finishTestRun();
    };

    function reportTestSuite() {
        reporter.reportTestSuite(getTestSuiteName());
    }

    function getTestSuiteName() {
        if (typeof(createTestSuite().getTestSuiteName) !== "function") {
            return testSuiteConstructor.name;
        }

        return createTestSuite().getTestSuiteName();
    }

    function createTestSuite() {
        return new testSuiteConstructor(assertions);
    }

    function runAllTests() {
        for (var testName in createTestSuite()) {
            if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
                handleTest(testName);
            }
        }
    }

    function handleTest(testName) {
        reportTest(testName);
        runTest(createTestSuite(), testName);
    }

    function reportTest(testName) {
        reporter.reportTest(testName);
    }

    function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
        try {
            testSuite[testName]();
        } catch (error) {
            if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
            status.failed = true;
        }
    }

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.failed) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>It already looks very nice. The only thing that I do not like about this object yet is that it has stateful properties and stateless properties. I like to have my objects separated by this concern. Let&rsquo;s extract <code>status</code> mutable property as a proper <code>TestSuiteRunStatus</code> object:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function TestSuiteRunStatus() {
    var failed = false;

    this.markAsFailed = function () {
        failed = true;
    };

    this.hasFailed = function () {
        return failed;
    };
}

function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
  // ...
  var status = new TestSuiteRunStatus();

  // ...
  function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
        try {
            testSuite[testName]();
        } catch (error) {
            if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
            status.markAsFailed();
        }
    }

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.hasFailed()) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I think we have finished the refactoring. Now we should verify that test suite exits with the code 0 when everything passes:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    this.testItExitsWithProcessCodeZero_onSuccess = function () {
        runTestSuite(function (t) {
            this.testFailure = function () {
                t.assertTrue(true);
            };
        }, {process: processSpy, silenceFailures: true});

        t.assertEqual(0, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal 0, but got: null

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.hasFailed()) return process.exit(1);
        process.exit(0);
    }
// =&gt; PASS
</code></pre>

<h2>Bottom Line</h2>

<p>I think we have finished implementing exit code reporting. The code can be found here: <a href="https://github.com/waterlink/BuildYourOwnTestingFrameworkPart5">https://github.com/waterlink/BuildYourOwnTestingFrameworkPart5</a></p>

<p>There is still a lot to go through. In a few next episodes we will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Report OK and FAIL for each test;</li>
<li>Output carefully formatted failures to the STDERR;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run multiple test suite files at once;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run in a browser (it is javascript after all).</li>
</ul>


<p>Stay tuned!</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HighScore Kata]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/30/highscore-kata/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-30T18:23:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/30/highscore-kata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, everyone. Today we will take a look into a little problem involving high scores in some sort of game. The game has only one high score and when current game&rsquo;s score exceeds that number, it gets updated. Example acceptance test would read like this:</p>

<p><strong>Given</strong> high score is <code>174</code><br/>
<strong>When</strong> player scores <code>191</code><br/>
<strong>Then</strong> high score is <code>191</code></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Current implementation stores high score in the web browser&rsquo;s local storage. This detail does not change the purpose of this Kata very much since any other platform and language can have its own analog of local storage (file system, in-memory or local database, application settings, etc.). <code>HighScore</code> object looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function Highscore() {
    // initially, load high score value from the local storage
    this.load();
}

Highscore.prototype.updateHighscore = function (score) {
    // check if we need to update high score
    if (score &gt; this.highscore) {
        this.highscore = score;
        this.save();
    }

    // render the high score in the
    // id="highscore" element in the browser
    $("#highscore").text("HIGHSCORE: " + this.highscore);
};

Highscore.prototype.load = function () {
    // localStorage is storing everything as strings,
    // so we need to convert it to number
    this.highscore = parseFloat(localStorage.highscore);
};

Highscore.prototype.save = function () {
    localStorage.highscore = this.highscore;
};
</code></pre>

<p>Task for the Kata:</p>

<ul>
<li>Write tests for this class.</li>
<li>Fix the bug: when a game is launched on the new client (without the high score stored), it renders <code>HIGHSCORE: NaN</code>. (<code>NaN</code> is javascript&rsquo;s abbreviation for &ldquo;not a number&rdquo;). <code>parseFloat</code> most probably is a culprit for this.</li>
<li>Extract storing mechanisms, so that class can be re-used with different storage mechanisms (for example local database, or external REST API).</li>
<li>Make all tests runnable outside of the context of the browser (for example, on <code>nodejs</code>).</li>
</ul>


<p>The focus of this Kata is on architectural boundaries, that this little innocent class spans.</p>

<p>Questions to ask yourself:</p>

<ul>
<li>How much distinct responsibilities this class has?</li>
<li>What architectural boundaries should I draw through this class?

<ul>
<li>How do I split this class according to these boundaries?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What is the easiest way and what is the proper way to make tests runnable outside of the context of the browser?</li>
<li>How would this code look like in different kinds of languages? (static, dynamic, object-oriented, functional, strong-typed, etc.).

<ul>
<li>And how the solution for the Kata will look like for these?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Next time we will take a look at one possible solution for this Kata. Try to solve it on your own, my dear reader, and please share the code and insights!</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don&rsquo;t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meet Duck Type]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/18/meet-duck-type/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-18T16:37:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/18/meet-duck-type</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Duck type</h2>

<p>Duck type is the concept in the domain of the type safety that represents objects, that pass a so-called &ldquo;Duck Test&rdquo;:</p>

<blockquote><p>If it looks like a duck, swims like a duck, and quacks like a duck, then it probably is a duck.</p></blockquote>

<p>In terms of programming language, it might look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function Duck() {
    this.swim = function (coordinates) { ... };
    this.quack = function (sentence) { ... };
}

function RoboDuck() {
    this.swim = function (coordinates) { ... };
    this.quack = function (sentence) { ... };
}

// .. and so on ..
</code></pre>

<!--more-->


<p>The point is that the public interface has methods <code>swim()</code> and <code>quack()</code>. This is how you identify the duck in a programming language. This concept is very similar to the concept of the <code>interface</code> in programming languages that have one, but it is not enforced in any way by the programming language.</p>

<p>Duck typing is mostly natural in dynamic languages, where it is possible to send any message to any object and the check if that is something possible will happen at runtime. In static languages, it is still possible to use duck typing via some sort of Reflection.</p>

<h3>Contract test for duck types</h3>

<p>In a dynamic language, it is important to make it obvious, that something is implementing certain duck type by writing one test suite for all implementers and executing it against them. For example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">[Duck, RoboDuck].forEach(function (duckType) {
    runTestSuite(function (t) {
        this.testItSwimsLikeADuck = function () {
            var duck = new duckType();
            duck.swim({x: 5, y: 7});
            t.assertThat(duck).swamTo({x: 5, y: 7});
        };

        this.testItQuacksLikeADuck = function () {
            var duck = new duckType();
            duck.quack("hello world");
            t.assertThat(duck).quacked("hello world");
        };
    });
});
</code></pre>

<p>This test suite has to go only through the Duck type public interface. If it is not possible to test behavior through it, one should test at least the function signatures, for example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testItSwimsLikeADuck = function () {
    var duck = new duckType();
    var swim = duck.swim;
    t.assertEqual("function", typeof(swim));
    t.assertEqual(1, swim.length);
};
</code></pre>

<p>Not doing contract tests for your ducks may result in a passing test suite and broken production code. For example, when one duck and its test suite have been updated, but others haven&rsquo;t.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don&rsquo;t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Test Doubles]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/18/introducing-test-doubles/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-18T16:31:48+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/18/introducing-test-doubles</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A test double is a test object or a test function, that looks and behaves like its production counterpart, but is actually a simplified version that reduces the complexity and enables simpler testing. One can represent all types of test double as an inheritance tree like this:</p>

<p><img src='//g.gravizo.com/g?
@startuml;
object Double;
object Dummy;
object Stub;
object Spy;
object Mock;
object Fake;
Double <|-- Dummy;
Double <|-- Fake;
Dummy <|-- Stub;
Stub <|-- Spy;
Spy <|-- Mock;
@enduml;
'/></p>

<p>Where <code>Double</code> is an abstract test double, which has no functionality - it is a general concept to talk about test doubles.</p>

<!--more-->


<p><code>Dummy</code> - is a test double, that is used to fill parameter lists, in cases where these parameters are not used by production code. Simplest <code>Dummy</code> would look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function ExampleDummyObject() {
  this.doSomething = function () {};

  this.getSomething = function () {
    return null;
  };
}

function exampleDummyFunction() {
  return null;
}

// Usage example in test
someObject.someMethod(dummyObject);
someFunction(exampleDummyFunction);
</code></pre>

<p><code>Stub</code> - is a test dummy, additionally, providing an indirect input for the production code from the test. &ldquo;Indirect&rdquo; means here via a method call on the stub object or a call of the stub function. For example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function ExampleStubObject() {
  var something = null;

  this.getSomething = function () {
    return something;
  };

  this.stubSomething = function(somethingValue) {
    something = somethingValue;
  };
}

var someValue = null;
function exampleStubFunction() {
  return someValue;
}

// Usage example in the test
stubObject.stubSomething("a value from the test");
anObject.aMethod(stubObject);

someValue = "a value from the test";
someFunction(exampleStubFunction);
</code></pre>

<p><div class="v2-subscribe--inline">
  





<div class="mc_embed_signup">
  <form action="//tddfellow.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34&amp;id=7f9f94015a" method="post" class="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <div class="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
      <h3>Want more articles like this delivered to your inbox?</h3>
      <div class="mc-field-group">
        <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
        <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true"><input type="text" name="b_535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34_7f9f94015a" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
        <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email mce-EMAIL" placeholder="Enter your email">
        <input type="submit" value="Subscribe" name="subscribe" class="button mc-embedded-subscribe">
      </div>
      <div class="">
        <em>(we respect your privacy, unsubscribe at any time)</em>
      </div>
    </div>
  </form>
</div>


</div>
</p>

<p><code>Spy</code> - is a test stub, additionally, verifying an indirect output of the production code, by asserting afterward, without having defined the expectations before the production code is executed. For example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function ExampleSpyObject(assertions) {
  var didSomethingWithName = null;
  var somethingValue = null;

  this.doSomethingWith = function (name) {
    didSomethingWithName = name;
    return somethingValue;
  };

  this.stubSomething = function (something) {
    somethingValue = something;
  };

  this.assertDidSomethingWithName = function(expectedName) {
    assertions.assertTrue(
      didSomethingWithName === expectedName,
      "Expected to do something with '" + expectedName + "'"
    )
  };
}

var withName = null;
var exampleValue = null;
function exampleSpyFunction(name) {
  withName = name;
  return exampleValue;
}

function verifyExampleSpyFunction(expectedName) {
  t.assertTrue(
    withName === expectedName,
    "Expected to be called with '" + expectedName + "'"
  )
}

// Usage in the test
spyObject.stubSomething("a value from the test");
anObject.aMethod(spyObject);
spyObject.assertDidSomethingWithName("helloWorld");

exampleValue = "a value from the test";
someFunction(exampleSpyFunction);
verifyExampleSpyFunction("helloWorld");
</code></pre>

<p><code>Mock</code> - is a stub, but the expectations are defined before the execution of the production code and it can verify itself after the execution. A simple example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function ExampleMockObject() {
  var expectedName = null;
  var fulfilled = false;
  var somethingValue = null;

  this.expectWillDoSomethingWithName = function (name) {
    expectedName = name;
  };

  this.doSomething = function (name) {
    assertions.assertTrue(
      name === expectedName,
      "Unexpected name '" + name + "',"
        + " expecting: '" + expectedName + "'"
    );

    fulfilled = true;
    return somethingValue;
  };

  this.stubSomething = function (value) {
    somethingValue = value;
  };

  this.verify = function () {
    assertions.assertTrue(
      fulfilled,
      "Expected to receive name '" + expectedName + "', "
        + "but got nothing"
    );
  };
}

// And the usage from the test:
mockObject.stubSomething("a value from the test");
mockObject.expectWillDoSomethingWithName("helloWorld");
anObject.aMethod(mockObject);
mockObject.verify();
</code></pre>

<p>Mocks can be much more complex (verifying order of messages, allowing multiple messages to be sent, etc.). So it is recommended to either:</p>

<ul>
<li>avoid them and use simpler test doubles, or</li>
<li>use a full-blown well-tested mocking framework.</li>
</ul>


<p>And if you do have to use your own custom mocks, please, write tests for them, since they can have a lot of logic inside of them.</p>

<p>And, finally, <code>Fake</code> - is a test double providing a simpler implementation used in the tests instead of the real thing. A good example is an in-memory database gateway, that behaves the same way the real one would, but it stores all the data in the memory. A very simple example:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function FakeDatabase() {
  var objects = {};

  this.save = function (id, object) {
    objects[id] = object;
  };

  this.findById = function (id) {
    return objects[id];
  };

  this.findByName = function (name) {
    for (var id in objects) {
      if (objects.hasOwnProperty(id)) {
        if (objects[id].name === name) {
          return objects[id];
        }
      }
    }

    return null;
  };
}
</code></pre>

<p>Obviously, fakes require full-blown testing for them. And if the real implementation is testable (even if it is slow), it is a good idea to have the same test suite for both: fake and real implementation. This way we can really be sure, that the fake behaves the same way as the real thing. And don&rsquo;t forget about the edge cases, for example, if the real thing can throw a <code>ConnectionError</code>, the fake should be able too (after being instructed to do so via a special method in the tests).</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don&rsquo;t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
