<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Javascript | That TDD Fellow | Tech Blog | Screencasts]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/categories/javascript/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-21T19:51:03+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Oleksii Fedorov (waterlink)]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Your Own Testing Framework. Part 6: Test Suite Does Not Run All Tests!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2017/03/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-6-test-suite-does-not-run-all-tests/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-13T23:13:28+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2017/03/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-6-test-suite-does-not-run-all-tests</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the new issue of &ldquo;Build Your Own Testing Framework&rdquo; series! When trying to implement better formatting, we have discovered that some of our test suites do not run all tests! Today we are going to fix that, and we will make sure that such test suite will fail if it didn&rsquo;t execute all tests.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>This article is the sixth one of the series “Build Your Own Testing Framework” so make sure to stick around for next parts! Find all posts of these series <a href="/blog/categories/build-your-own-testing-framework/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Shall we get started?</p>

<h2>Verify All Tests Run</h2>

<p>We will start from the <code>RunTestSuiteTest</code> and run the test suite with the single test. Then we are going to assert that for that the test with the name <code>testOk</code> has been reported as passing:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// test/RunTestSuiteTest.js

this.testItOutputsOkForThePassingTest = function () {
    runTestSuite(function (t) {
        this.testOk = function () {
            t.assertTrue(true);
        };
    }, {reporter: reporter});

    reporter.assertHasReportedPassingTest("testOk");
};
</code></pre>

<p>If we run this test suite, we can see that only one test executes!</p>

<pre><code>RunTestSuiteTest
    testItCallsAllTestMethods

Process finished with exit code 0
</code></pre>

<p>Oh, that is interesting. This test suite does not run. Upon investigating, it turns out, that <code>process.exit(0)</code> is being called during the <code>runTestSuite(...)</code> function run. That is because of the latest feature that we have implemented - &ldquo;exit with an appropriate exit code (zero for success, and one for failure).&rdquo; We should be able to fix that by providing the process spy in the options of the <code>runTestSuite</code> function that we are calling from the inside of the individual tests in the <code>RunTestSuiteTest</code> test suite. And we ought to alleviate this kind of mistake somehow - we need a mechanism that would alert us if not all tests have been run. Maybe something like <code>verifyAllTestsRun: true</code> option for the <code>runTestSuite</code>. For that let&rsquo;s write a test:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testVerifyAllTestsRun = function () {
    t.assertThrow("Expected all tests to run", function () {

        runTestSuite(function SuiteWithTwoTests(t) {

            this.testWithRunTestSuite = function () {
                runTestSuite(function (t) {
                    this.testOne = function () {};
                }, {reporter: reporter});
            };

            this.testThatShouldAlsoRun = function () {};

        }, {reporter: reporter,
            process: process,
            verifyAllTestsRun: true});

    });
};
</code></pre>

<p>That might be a bit complex at first. Let&rsquo;s take a closer look how this test is supposed to work:</p>

<ol>
<li>First of all, we do assert that there was an assertion failure about all tests required to run.</li>
<li>Inside of the action for this assertion we create and run the new test suite with two tests:

<ul>
<li>test with the <code>runTestSuite</code> without process spy provided</li>
<li>empty test that should also execute</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ol>


<p>If we run this test, it will pass. That is unexpected because we wanted it to fail. Apparently, most inner <code>runTestSuite</code> is doing <code>process.exit(0)</code>.</p>

<p>For that to work, we will need to be able to provide a hook into <code>process.exit(code)</code> function. For that, we would need to create a <code>SimpleProcess</code> class, that allows installation of such hooks. Let&rsquo;s test-drive it!</p>

<h3><code>process.exit</code> with hooks</h3>

<p>First, we should start from the normal behavior without any hooks:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// test/SimpleProcessTest.js
var runTestSuite = require("../src/TestingFramework");
var SimpleProcess = require("../src/TestingFramework").SimpleProcess;
var ProcessSpy = require("./ProcessSpy");

runTestSuite(function SimpleProcessTest(t) {
    this.testWithoutHooks = function () {
        var globalProcess = new ProcessSpy();
        var process = new SimpleProcess(globalProcess);

        process.exit(0);

        t.assertEqual(0, globalProcess.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>When running this test, we will get a failure about <code>SimpleProcess</code> being undefined. So let&rsquo;s define it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/TestingFramework.js

// ...
// define the class itself
function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {

}

// ..
// and don't forget to export it
module.exports.SimpleProcess = SimpleProcess;
</code></pre>

<p>If we run our test suite now, we will get an error <code>TypeError: process.exit is not a function</code>. To fix that failure we will have to define the <code>exit(code)</code> method on our newly created class <code>SimpleProcess</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {
    this.exit = function (code) {

    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>After doing that we will get an assertion failure <code>Error: Expected to equal 0, but got: null</code>, as expected. To make the test pass, it would be enough to call <code>globalProcess.exit(0)</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.exit = function (code) {
    globalProcess.exit(0);
};
</code></pre>

<p>If we run our test suite now, we will get no failures. That is great! Now, we can see that <code>globalProcess.exit(0)</code> is probably not exactly what we want to have there. We ought to pass the <code>code</code> parameter to the <code>exit</code> function. To test-drive this properly, we will have to triangulate, i.e.: add another test with the different value of the <code>code</code> parameter:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testWithoutHooks_andDifferentExitCode = function () {
    var globalProcess = new ProcessSpy();
    var process = new SimpleProcess(globalProcess);

    process.exit(1);

    t.assertEqual(1, globalProcess.hasExitedWithCode);
};
</code></pre>

<p>That fails as expected: <code>Error: Expected to equal 1, but got: 0</code>. To make it pass we can either write some weird &ldquo;if&rdquo; statement or we could pass the <code>code</code> parameter to the <code>globalProcess.exit</code> function. The second option is simpler. According to the third rule of test-driven development, we should go for it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.exit = function (code) {
    globalProcess.exit(code);
};
</code></pre>

<p>That change makes our test suite pass. We probably should refactor the test suite to reduce the level of the duplication by extracting common variables from the tests:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function SimpleProcessTest(t) {
    var globalProcess = new ProcessSpy();
    var process = new SimpleProcess(globalProcess);

    this.testWithoutHooks = function () {
        process.exit(0);

        t.assertEqual(0, globalProcess.hasExitedWithCode);
    };

    this.testWithoutHooks_andDifferentExitCode = function () {
        process.exit(1);

        t.assertEqual(1, globalProcess.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>At that point, we should move on to tests for the hook installation functionality. Because right now we need only at most one hook we will not support multiple hooks at the same time - only one:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testCanInstallOneHook = function () {
    var aSpy = t.spy();

    process.installHook(aSpy);
    process.exit(0);

    aSpy.assertCalled();
};
</code></pre>

<p>When we run this test, it fails because <code>installHook</code> function is not defined: <code>TypeError: process.installHook is not a function</code>. So we should define it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {
    // ..
    this.installHook = function (aHook) {

    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>Upon running these tests, we get <code>Error: Expected to be called</code> because we didn&rsquo;t call this hook yet. The simplest way to make it pass is to just call the hook from the <code>installHook</code> function:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {
    // ...
    this.installHook = function (aHook) {
        aHook();
    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>While that will make the tests pass it is not the behavior that we are after. To drive out the correct behavior, we ought to check that the function is being called only after <code>process.exit(..)</code>, not earlier. For that we will need to have a sanity-check assertion:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testCanInstallOneHook = function () {
    var aSpy = t.spy();

    process.installHook(aSpy);
    aSpy.assertNotCalled();

    process.exit(0);

    aSpy.assertCalled();
};
</code></pre>

<p>That fails as expected with the error <code>Error: Expected not to be called</code>. To make it pass we need to store the function in the variable and call it from the <code>process.exit(..)</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {
    var hook = null;

    this.exit = function (code) {
        if (hook !== null)
            hook();

        globalProcess.exit(code);
    };

    this.installHook = function (aHook) {
        hook = aHook;
    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>All the tests pass now! Finally, we want to be able to uninstall the hook, so let&rsquo;s write the test for it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">this.testCanUninstallTheHook = function () {
    var aSpy = t.spy();

    process.installHook(aSpy);
    process.uninstallHook();

    process.exit(0);

    aSpy.assertNotCalled();
};
</code></pre>

<p>To make it work it is enough to introduce this function and set <code>hook</code> variable back to <code>null</code> in it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function SimpleProcess(globalProcess) {
    // ...
    this.uninstallHook = function () {
        hook = null;
    };
}
</code></pre>

<p>And all the tests will pass. Now we, also, want to replace the default value for the <code>options.process</code> option with the instance of <code>SimpleProcess</code> object. And all the tests should work as they were working before:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var simpleProcess = new SimpleProcess(global.process);

function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    // ...

    var process = options.process || simpleProcess;
    // instead of just "global.process"

    // ...
}
</code></pre>

<h3>Installing the &ldquo;verify all tests run&rdquo; hook</h3>

<p>Now, we can get back to our &ldquo;verify all tests run&rdquo; test. It still doesn&rsquo;t fail as expected, so we need to install the hook, count all tests, count tests that had already run and compare them in the hook:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    // ...
    var verifyAllTestsRun = options.verifyAllTestsRun || false;
    var testCount = 0;
    var testRun = 0;

    this.invoke = function () {
        if (verifyAllTestsRun)
            installVerifyAllTestsRunHook();  // &lt;---

        reportTestSuite();
        countAllTests();                     // &lt;---
        runAllTests();
        finishTestRun();
    };

    function installVerifyAllTestsRunHook() {
        simpleProcess.installHook(function () {
            if (testRun &lt; testCount) {
                throw new Error("Expected all tests to run");
            }
        });
    }

    // ...

    function countAllTests() {
        for (var testName in createTestSuite())
            if (testName.match(/^test/))
                testCount++;
    }

    // ...

    function handleTest(testName) {
        testRun++;                            // &lt;---
        reportTest(testName);
        runTest(createTestSuite(), testName);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, this throws an error <code>Expected all tests to run</code> and finishes the test fully without reaching our <code>assertThrow(..)</code> assertion. That happens because we catch this error in the function <code>runTest</code>, where we mark the test as failed, log the error and ignore the error object itself from there. One way to solve this problem is to have a particular error, that can propagate up the stack:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function installVerifyAllTestsRunHook() {
    simpleProcess.installHook(function () {
        if (testRun &lt; testCount) {
            var error = new Error("Expected all tests to run");
            error.bubbleUp = true;
            throw error;
        }
    });
}

// ...

function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
    try {
        testSuite[testName]();
    } catch (error) {
        if (error.bubbleUp) throw error;  // &lt;---
        if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
        status.markAsFailed();
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now our current test is passing, and the next test is failing with the error <code>Expected all tests to run</code>. That happens because we have not uninstalled the hook as soon as it has triggered. Let&rsquo;s do that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function installVerifyAllTestsRunHook() {
    simpleProcess.installHook(function () {
        if (testRun &lt; testCount) {
            simpleProcess.uninstallHook();   // &lt;---

            var error = new Error("Expected all tests to run");
            error.bubbleUp = true;
            throw error;
        }
    });
}
</code></pre>

<p>That makes the next test run, succeed and exit immediately after that with error code zero. Let&rsquo;s see what will happen if we put <code>verifyAllTestsRun: true</code> on the top test suite here:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function RunTestSuiteTest(t) {
    // ...
}, {verifyAllTestsRun: true});
</code></pre>

<p>That doesn&rsquo;t work because we re-install different hook inside of this test and as soon as this test finishes, we uninstall it. So we have two ways out of this situation: allow multiple hooks, or move that single test to its own test suite file. I think the second options is much simpler. Also, we will add the test for the negative case, where all tests run correctly (when we provide proper process spy):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// test/VerifyAllTestsRunTest.js
var runTestSuite = require("../src/TestingFramework");
var ReporterSpy = require("./ReporterSpy");
var ProcessSpy = require("./ProcessSpy");

runTestSuite(function VerifyAllTestsRunTest(t) {
    var reporter = new ReporterSpy(t);
    var process = new ProcessSpy(t);

    this.testVerifyAllTestsRun = function () {
        t.assertThrow("Expected all tests to run", function () {

            runTestSuite(function SuiteWithTwoTests(t) {

                this.testWithRunTestSuite = function () {
                    runTestSuite(function (t) {
                        this.testOne = function () {};
                    }, {reporter: reporter});
                };

                this.testThatShouldAlsoRun = function () {};

            }, {reporter: reporter,
                process: process,
                verifyAllTestsRun: true});

        });
    };

    this.testVerifyAllTestsRun_withoutFailure = function () {
        t.assertNotThrow(function () {

            runTestSuite(function SuiteWithTwoTests(t) {

                this.testWithRunTestSuite = function () {
                    runTestSuite(function (t) {
                        this.testOne = function () {};
                    }, {reporter: reporter,
                        process: process});
                };

                this.testThatShouldAlsoRun = function () {};

            }, {reporter: reporter,
                process: process,
                verifyAllTestsRun: true});

        });
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>And this new test suite passes as expected. Just to double-check that these tests verify anything, we can break them (change expected error message and change <code>assertNotThrow</code> to <code>assertThrow</code>) and see if there is a failure and if it looks as expected:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// was: t.assertThrow("some error", ...);
t.assertThrow("some error", function () {
    // ...
});
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal some error,
//    but got: Expected all tests to run

// was: t.assertNotThrow(...);
t.assertThrow("some error", function () {
    // ...
});
// =&gt; Error: Expected to throw an error,
//    but nothing was thrown
</code></pre>

<p>And it fails as expected, which means that our refactored tests still work as they should.</p>

<blockquote><p>We have just applied a neat technique here: whenever we do a major refactoring in tests, we need to make sure they are still functioning correctly. For that, we break every single one of them (by changing the assertion or breaking the production code). Then we see if they fail as we expect them to. When they don&rsquo;t, we know that refactoring didn&rsquo;t quite work.</p></blockquote>

<h3>Fixing test suites to run all tests</h3>

<p>Now we can go back to the <code>RunTestSuiteTest</code> and see if it works as expected without that test. And it does: <code>Error: Expected all tests to run</code>. To fix that we need to provide a process spy in every inner call to <code>runTestSuite</code>. For that we will first extract <code>{reporter: reporter}</code> as a common variable of the test suite:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var options = {reporter: reporter};

// ...
// all the inner calls to "runTestSuite":
runTestSuite(function(t) {
    // ...
}, options);
</code></pre>

<p>And to make the error go away, we now can create a process spy and provide it through options:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var process = new ProcessSpy(t);
var options = {
    reporter: reporter,
    process: process
};
</code></pre>

<p>If we run tests now, they all pass. And we can see that they all execute. Now we just need to double-check that all tests, that have inner calls to <code>runTestSuite</code> have <code>verifyAllTestsRun</code> option enabled. The only other test suite is the <code>FailureTest</code>. Adding the option does not produce a failure because this test suite already uses process spy in all inner calls to <code>runTestSuite</code>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Today we learned that it is tricky to work with <code>process.exit</code> or any function that can exit our program in the middle of the test. Such functions need to be mocked out completely inside of the tests. Also, we learned that it is possible to make sure we don&rsquo;t forget to do that. That is quite important because, if we do forget, everything runs smoothly, and we don&rsquo;t know that we made a mistake.</p>

<p>There is still a lot to go through. In a few next episodes we will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Report OK and FAIL for each test;</li>
<li>Output carefully formatted failures to the STDERR;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run multiple test suite files at once;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run in a browser (it is javascript after all).</li>
</ul>


<p>See you reading the next exciting article of the series: &ldquo;Formatting the Output&rdquo;!</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Test-Driven Development With Javascript: Laws of TDD]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2017/02/03/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-laws-of-tdd/"/>
    <updated>2017-02-03T22:19:40+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2017/02/03/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-laws-of-tdd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Level: Beginner</strong></p>

<p>Today we are going to learn the basic principles behind the Test-Driven Development Discipline. We will learn three rules of TDD. We will learn what are the benefits of doing Test-Driven Development. And we will take a look at the example application of these laws.</p>

<div about='https://farm8.static.flickr.com/7430/12500965335_75001934e7.jpg'>
  <img xmlns:dct='http://purl.org/dc/terms/' href='http://purl.org/dc/dcmitype/StillImage' rel='dct:type' src='http://www.tddfellow.com/images/learning-tdd-with-js/feedback.png' alt='feedback by Sonti Malonti, on Flickr' title='feedback by Sonti Malonti, on Flickr' border='0'/>
  <br/>
  <span class="img-attribution">
    &quot;
    <a href='https://www.flickr.com/photos/sontimalonti/12500965335/' target='_blank'>feedback</a>
    &quot;&nbsp;
    (<a rel='license' href='https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0/' target='_blank'>CC BY-SA 2.0</a>)
    &nbsp;by&nbsp;<a xmlns:cc='http://creativecommons.org/ns#' rel='cc:attributionURL' property='cc:attributionName' href='https://www.flickr.com/people/sontimalonti/' target='_blank'>Sonti Malonti</a>
  </span>
</div>




<!-- more -->


<p>Articles of these series have exercises and going through them would make for more effective learning. Also, if you feel stuck with these exercises, fell free to shoot me an email or get in touch on Twitter: @waterlink000.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Learning Test-Driven Development with Javascript&rdquo; is a series of articles and you, my dear reader, can shape the content by providing an invaluable feedback. To do that, shoot me an email - <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#111;&#58;&#x6f;&#108;&#x65;&#107;&#x73;&#105;&#105;&#64;&#x74;&#x64;&#100;&#x66;&#101;&#108;&#108;&#x6f;&#x77;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#x6d;&#46;">&#111;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x6b;&#x73;&#105;&#x69;&#x40;&#116;&#100;&#x64;&#102;&#101;&#108;&#108;&#111;&#x77;&#x2e;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;&#46;</a></p>

<h2>Basics of Test-Driven Development</h2>

<p>A test is a single program, procedure or function, that executes our system under the test and verifies that it works as expected. The system under the test is any other program, part of the program or library, procedure or function. The system under the test is called SUT for short.</p>

<p>SUT is the code that executes with a purpose of satisfying needs of our end users. Using the term &ldquo;end user&rdquo; we mean actual people using our system via the user interface (graphical and non-graphical), and other automated systems using our system via application programming interface (for short, API). A different term for the &ldquo;end user&rdquo; is &ldquo;consumer of the system.&rdquo; Another term for the SUT is &ldquo;production code&rdquo; - we are going to use the latter, as it is used in Test-Driven Development much more often.</p>

<p>Test-Driven Development is based on a simple concept of writing production code only when there is a failing test that demands that production code for it to pass.</p>

<p>We call a test failing when there is some error happening when we execute it. Possible failures are the following: there is a syntax error, or code does not compile, or there is a runtime failure during test setup or production code execution, or there is an assertion error. The assertion failure is the particular kind of error that happens during the final phase of the test, where we are verifying the outcomes after running the production code under the test. An assertion error signals that the production code executed successfully, but it produced incorrect results or changed the state of the system in a wrong fashion.</p>

<p>We call a test passing when there are no errors happen when we execute it. We, also, call the failing test &ldquo;a red test&rdquo; and we call the passing test &ldquo;a green test.&rdquo; That is because we can not deliver the code to our customers or consumers when there are &ldquo;red&rdquo; tests - think of red traffic light, and we are free to go when all the tests are &ldquo;green&rdquo; - think of green traffic light. Most of the testing tools and frameworks format their output to present failing tests in the red color and passing tests in the green color.</p>

<p>Multiple tests aiming to test single SUT or a particular feature of the system are usually called test suite. Depending on the context, test suite could mean that collection of tests all testing the same thing, or it could mean all tests of the entire system. For example, in the sentence &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s read <code>User</code> class&#8217; test suite&rdquo; that phrase means a collection of tests testing class <code>User</code>. On the other hand, in the sentence &ldquo;Let&rsquo;s run the whole test suite and see if we can deploy that right now&rdquo; that phrase means all tests of the entire system. The latter, sometimes, is called &ldquo;suite of tests.&rdquo;</p>

<p>When the system behaves in an unexpected way, and the expected behavior was previously defined or present in the code, it is called a &ldquo;bug.&rdquo; For example, the behavior that is specified by the development team and not implemented correctly considered a bug. The behavior that is defined by the development team and implemented correctly, but now it is not working, considered a bug. And, finally, the behavior that was not defined may or may not be considered as a bug. The latter depends on the produced results - if it harms or brings any value. This phenomenon is called a &ldquo;bug&rdquo; for historical reasons: the first bug in computing was a real bug, that stuck in the computer&rsquo;s hardware and was causing short circuits which made the computer misbehave.</p>

<h2>Three Rules of Test-Driven Development</h2>

<p>In the core of Test-Driven Development there are three steps that we need to follow:</p>

<ol>
<li>We start with a failing test. We consider any error a failure, including compilation and syntax errors. Meaning, that our first test for any part of the production code will fail for the reason that there is no production code to execute yet. For example class, method or function is undefined.</li>
<li>Then, we resolve the failure by writing the production code. For example: in the case of missing class, we would create a class; in the event of a missing method, we would create it; and in the instance of a failing assertion error, we would fix the logic to pass the test.</li>
<li>We write no more than the simplest production code, which makes our current failing test pass, and, also, still passes all other tests.</li>
</ol>


<p>We repeat these steps over and over until we finish the implementation of the system under the test. Strictly following these steps will lock us in a very tight loop, where we will be switching between test code and production code all the time: write one or two lines of the test code and write or change one or two lines of the production code, repeat. This cycle is, probably, twenty or thirty seconds long. It, of course, depends on how fast we can run our tests. Ideally, we want our test suite for the current system under the test to run as fast as one clap of hands, or blink of an eye.</p>

<h2>Feedback Loop Benefits</h2>

<p>This tight cycle gives us following benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Alerts us to the mistakes we do while coding immediately. Usually, it is enough to do one or two &ldquo;Undo&rdquo; commands in our editor to get back to the &ldquo;green&rdquo; state of the system - when all our tests are passing (occasionally, except for the last test we have added, as we will undo the incorrect implementation for it).</li>
<li>Provides the safety net from bugs for the future development thanks to the fact, that no single line of production code is written other than to pass a failing test. Meaning, that whenever production code is broken in any fashion, there is a test that will point it out via failure. When adding new features or modifying the behavior of the existing ones, we might inadvertently introduce a bug. Our suite of tests will detect that bug as soon as we run all our tests, which we would certainly do during development and, especially, before the deployment or release of our systems. This is, basically, a near 100% test coverage. Surely, there are subtle and complex bugs that involve whole sub-systems and 3rd-party systems to come together in some special edge case to appear - rarely, such bugs are not prevented by Test-Driven Development. Of course, we are talking about 1-3 such bugs per year - this is much better than having a bug tracker, that contains thousands of unresolved bugs. Who said it was a good idea to have a database that stores the bugs in our system? - When we apply TDD correctly, and our bug counts are so small, as 1-3 per year, we should treat bugs as &ldquo;Red Alerts&rdquo; and concentrate all the effort on shooting them down. Writing a test for these bugs when we already figured them out allows us to programmatically prove, that the system, indeed, does misbehave in a certain edge case, and prevents this bug from reoccurring after we have fixed it.</li>
<li>Gives the confidence to refactor freely and ruthlessly. Essentially, allows changing the software design of the system on the go without applying the big design upfront (BDUF). Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example. Imagine, we have a system with a perfect design and without any tests. Over time the design will degrade until the code becomes nearly impossible to work with. Now, imagine, we have a system with bad design and close to 100% test coverage. Over time we can improve the design of the application gradually while responding to the changes in the needs of our end users. And we will be faster as the time passes.</li>
<li>Makes the development team always ready to deploy. While practicing test-driven development, development teams will keep latest implemented features in the version control system for the source code in the state, that is well-known to be &ldquo;green.&rdquo; This condition of the system is deliverable to the end users with one push of the button. That, also, enables teams to do continuous delivery: as soon as the code is checked-in in the version control system (VCS), it is going to be automatically deployed to production and our end users will get the value out of it sooner.</li>
<li>Promotes simplicity and alleviates the scope creep. &ldquo;Oh, we don&rsquo;t need that yet&rdquo; is the most used phrase in the vocabulary of the typical test-driven development practitioner. Tests that we write specify only the useful functionality that we need to deliver the value to our end users. These tests don&rsquo;t talk about performance optimizations, security concerns, rare edge cases, &ldquo;re-usable&rdquo; abstractions (that, usually, are harder to understand and are difficult to re-use), etc. These things need to be implemented only when there is an actual end user value to be achieved, or the system is obviously running slower than it should, or there is an actual security concern. In that case, a very specific test (or tests) will be written to drive out that additional functionality. Since the most software development cost is in the maintenance of the existing functionality leaving out as much functionality (and code) as possible is a good idea.</li>
<li>Promotes cleaner interfaces. As in test-driven development, we have to write the usage example before we implement (or even design) the API in the production code, it will be optimized for ease and clarity of use and less so with the internal implementation details of that production code. Generally speaking, test-driven production code is easier to use and understand.</li>
<li>Tests that call the production code serve as usage examples of that code. Essentially, in a test-driven code base, to know how a particular API can be used, it is enough to read and understand its test suite. These tests are the perfect low-level documentation for the APIs in our code base that developers can understand and read best. And that documentation is so precise that it can be executed and verified that it is still in sync with the actual code it is describing. Therefore this documentation is always up-to-date.</li>
</ul>


<p>The most important of these benefits is the confidence to make any change to the software and know in one minute or two, if that change is good to be delivered to the end user or not, with a simple push of the button. No quality assurance (QA) manual testing cycles are required. Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example of the application of three rules of test-driven development. We will start from a very simple example, so that we don&rsquo;t have to touch more advanced TDD techniques.</p>

<h2>English Numbers Kata</h2>

<blockquote><p><strong>Given</strong> an integer number<br/>
<strong>When</strong> I call the system with that number<br/>
<strong>Then</strong> I receive a string representation of that number in an English language</p>

<p>For example:</p>

<ul>
<li>for number <code>37</code> I receive <code>"thirty-seven"</code></li>
<li>for number <code>-17451</code> I receive <code>"minus seventeen thousand four hundred fifty-one"</code></li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>According to the first rule of TDD, we have to start the implementation from the test. In test-driven development it is important to start from the simplest tests, that can be implemented via a small, simple change to production code. For example: with number zero we expect the result to be &ldquo;zero.&rdquo; When writing the first test for the new functionality we are going to design its API. In our case we are going to come up with the function name and its argument list:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">describe("toEnglishNumber", function() {
    it("converts 0 to zero", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 0;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);
    });
});
</code></pre>

<p>As soon as we write <code>toEnglishNumber(number)</code> we have designed the function&rsquo;s signature, at least, for the single simplest case. Also, the test suite is failing now, because <code>toEnglishNumber</code> is not a function - in fact, it is undefined. That means that we have entered the red stage of test driven development and according to the second rule of TDD we have to switch back to the production code. And according to the third rule, we have to write just enough of it to make the failing test pass. That means writing the simplest and easiest code possible to make it succeed. In this case, we could just return nothing (<code>null</code> in javascript):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    return null;
}
</code></pre>

<p>This is going to turn our test suite back to the green stage. At this point it is a good idea to look at both test code and production code and see if there are any opportunities for refactoring, such as better names, extracting methods/functions, clarifying variable names, de-duplication, etc. Because we are currently in a green state, we can safely apply any refactoring, automated or manual, and see if it was successful by running the test again. If for some reason, the test is failing after the refactoring, we always have an option to CTRL/CMD+Z back to the green state, back to safety. At this point, we have finished applying one cycle of rules of TDD. Now we need to start over. We go back to our test code. There we extend the existing test to be more specific. Or we add more tests. Since we didn&rsquo;t finish writing the test yet - we have only &ldquo;arrange&rdquo; and &ldquo;act&rdquo; parts, and we are missing the &ldquo;assert&rdquo; part of the test, - we ought to extend the current test to make it more specific. So what can we assert about the result of the <code>toEnglishNumber</code> call? We probably ought to return the string &ldquo;zero&rdquo;, aren&rsquo;t we? So, let&rsquo;s make an appropriate assertion:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 0 to zero", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 0;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "zero";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected);
});
</code></pre>

<p>If we run our tests right now, they will fail. We should take a careful look at the failure and see if the failure message is readable and it is what we expected. In the current situation, we will receive an assertion failure, telling us that <code>null</code> was not equal to &ldquo;zero.&rdquo; Imagine now, that we are working on some other feature and we are not in the context of the English number conversion feature. What would be our reaction, when we run this test and see this failure? - We will probably be confused for a moment and will resort to jump to the line in the source code of the test suite that produces that error and try to understand what happened there. That is a huge context switch, and it will disrupt our current flow. So we can do better and make the failure much more readable by just adding a small thing - a cue, what that <code>null</code> was supposed to be: &ldquo;english number&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
</code></pre>

<p>In Jasmine, the second argument to the <code>toEqual</code> matching function is the description of the failure. I think our test looks great, and so is the failure in the test output. And because we are having a good failing test, according to the second rule, we don&rsquo;t have to write any of test code. Now, we should make the test pass according to the third rule. And what would be the simplest way to make it work? - Return &ldquo;zero&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    return "zero";
}
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, we should look out for the refactoring opportunities, and I don&rsquo;t think there are any yet. So let&rsquo;s start the cycle over. To apply the first rule, we might just copy the existing test and change the input and the expected output accordingly. In that case, we would want to test another simple one-digit number - &ldquo;one&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 1 to one", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 1;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "one";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>Now, because the test is failing, we apply the second rule and switch back to the production code. To make the test pass, according to the third rule, we will need to introduce the simplest change possible: in that case, an &ldquo;if&rdquo; statement (and we will use <code>===</code> instead of <code>==</code> for comparison to avoid implicit type conversions in javascript):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number === 1) {
        return "one";
    }

    return "zero";
}
</code></pre>

<p>That is going to make all our tests pass. If we continue adding tests for the single-digit numbers while following these three rules, we will wind up with something like that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number === 1) {
        return "one";
    }

    if (number === 2) {
        return "two";
    }

    if (number === 3) {
        return "three";
    }

    if (number === 4) {
        return "four";
    }

    if (number === 5) {
        return "five";
    }

    if (number === 6) {
        return "six";
    }

    if (number === 7) {
        return "seven";
    }

    if (number === 8) {
        return "eight";
    }

    if (number === 9) {
        return "nine";
    }

    return "zero";
}
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, we can see a clear pattern: one-to-one correspondence of a single-digit integer to the string. This code can be simplified as a pre-defined array of strings at the corresponding indices:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var singleDigitNumbers = [
    "zero",
    "one",
    "two",
    "three",
    "four",
    "five",
    "six",
    "seven",
    "eight",
    "nine"
];
</code></pre>

<p>We also include string &ldquo;zero&rdquo; in that array because <code>return "zero"</code> is only happening when the number is equal to zero since we don&rsquo;t have any other tests right now - only from zero to nine. And the function itself will look much simpler:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    return singleDigitNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Since we are done with the refactoring, we should proceed using the first rule of test-driven development, which means we need to write a test that fails. So let&rsquo;s increase the complexity of our tests and go for teen numbers. We&rsquo;ll start from ten:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 10 to ten", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 10;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "ten";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>That will fail because so far our production code tries to fetch a string representation of the english number from the array using the number itself as an index. At the index ten, we don&rsquo;t have anything, so our function returns nothing. According to the second rule of test-driven development, we need to switch to production code to make it pass. There are a few ways to fix the current problem: add specific if statement to the production code, or add a string &ldquo;ten&rdquo; to the array. Second seems to be simpler, and we know that we can do it for the teen numbers because they can not be composed of any other small parts. So, according to the third rule, we should go for it because it is a much simpler solution:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var singleDigitNumbers = [
    // ...
    "ten"
];
</code></pre>

<p>That makes our tests pass. And I think we have a refactoring opportunity: variable name <code>singleDigitNumbers</code> does not make any sense anymore - it contains not only single digit numbers, but, also, number &ldquo;ten,&rdquo; which is a two-digit number. So what is common between single digit numbers and ten? They are simple numbers, i.e.: can not be composed out of other english number string representations. Let&rsquo;s just call them <code>simpleNumbers</code> in this case:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var simpleNumbers = [
    // ...
];

function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>After making this refactoring, we need not forget to run the test suite to see if we didn&rsquo;t make a mistake. When we run it, then all our tests pass. So we can go back to the first rule of test-driven development again. Going through this cycle again for a few times will produce tests for numbers from eleven to nineteen. The production code will only have those numbers&#8217; english string representations added to the <code>simpleNumbers</code> array:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var simpleNumbers = [
    "zero", "one", "two", "three", "four",
    "five", "six", "seven", "eight", "nine",

    "ten", "eleven", "twelve", "thirteen", "fourteen",
    "fifteen", "sixteen", "seventeen", "eighteen", "nineteen"
];

function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now it is time to introduce the concept of a complex number, such as twenty-three. It is a number that consists of the &ldquo;tens&rdquo; part and single-digit part. According to the first rule we have to start with the failing test, and I think we should just go for the number twenty-three:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 23 to twenty-three", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 23;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "twenty-three";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>If we run our test suite, that test will fail. According to the second rule of test-driven development, now we have to switch to the production code. According to the third rule, we will have to choose the simplest code that makes this test pass (and doesn&rsquo;t break any other test). In our case, we have multiple options, which are similar in their simplicity. One of them is to return &ldquo;twenty-three&rdquo; if the number is greater than or equal to twenty:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        return "twenty-three";
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>If we run our test suite, all tests will pass. Now we should see if there are any opportunities for making the code more readable and easier to understand. While the whole if statement returning a constant might feel strange, there is a concept that we can already give a name to in there: &ldquo;three.&rdquo; We already can obtain a string &ldquo;three&rdquo; from number three using the method <code>toEnglishNumber(number)</code>. Let&rsquo;s try this refactoring:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        return "twenty-" + toEnglishNumber(3);
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>That code now looks interesting. And it passes all its tests. Since, of course, we are not done yet with the implementation, according to the first rule of test-driven development, we ought to write another failing test. And we have a multitude of choices what it could be, we can just come up with other random two-digit number, such as forty-two, or we could leave the &ldquo;twenty-&rdquo; part in and change the &ldquo;three&rdquo; part to &ldquo;seven,&rdquo; for example. Also, we could change &ldquo;twenty-&rdquo; part to &ldquo;thirty-.&rdquo; Generally, in test-driven development it is better to go for the test, that will cause the smallest change to the production code, - later we will explore more on why that is. So, we could go for twenty-seven, as it will cause the smallest change to our production code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 27 to twenty-seven", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 27;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "twenty-seven";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>This test is failing, as expected. According to the second rule, we have to switch to the production code and make it pass. Also, the simplest change (third rule) that we could do is to change &ldquo;3&rdquo; to the last digit of the number, the remainder of the division by ten - &ldquo;number % 10&rdquo;:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        return "twenty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now if we run our test suite all the tests will pass. &ldquo;The remainder of division by ten&rdquo; part looks right and &ldquo;twenty-&rdquo; constant still feels like it is not gonna work for every two-digit number. I think it is time to write a new failing test (first rule). That will be the test that will prove that &ldquo;twenty-&rdquo; is not correct code. In that case, we just need to change the first digit of the number so that we could go for forty-two:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 42 to forty-two", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 42;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "forty-two";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>As soon as we finish writing the assertion we will have a test failure: we are returning &ldquo;twenty-two&rdquo; instead of &ldquo;forty-two.&rdquo; So it is time to switch to the production code (second rule). And we need to write just enough of it to make this test pass (third rule). We can do that by having yet another if statement:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        if (number / 10 == 2) {
            return "twenty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
        }

        return "forty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>And this will make the test pass. It looks very similar to what we had with one-digit numbers, where we had an &ldquo;if&rdquo; statement checking that some value is equal to some number and returning an appropriate string. That is where we converted it to an array with string values, and in the function, we were fetching these strings by their index. To see if that pattern applies here we could write another similar test that will make us write another if statement:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">it("converts 39 to thirty-nine", function() {
    // ARRANGE
    var number = 39;

    // ACT
    var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

    // ASSERT
    var expected = "thirty-nine";
    expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
});
</code></pre>

<p>And this fails as expected because our production code in no case can return &ldquo;thirty-.&rdquo; So let&rsquo;s write the simplest if statement to make it pass. Also, to make it uniform, we would wrap &ldquo;forty-&rdquo; case in its appropriate if statement as a refactoring after we have a passing test suite:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        if (number / 10 == 2) {
            return "twenty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
        }

        if (number / 10 == 3) {
            return "thirty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
        }

        if (number / 10 == 4) {
            return "forty-" + toEnglishNumber(number % 10);
        }
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Certainly, there is a fair bit of duplication right now: &ldquo;number / 10&rdquo; and &ldquo;number % 10&rdquo;. Let&rsquo;s extract them as variables. Also, let&rsquo;s extract &ldquo;twenty&rdquo;, &ldquo;thirty&rdquo;, &ldquo;forty&rdquo; and &ldquo;toEnglishNumber(lastDigit)&rdquo; parts as variables:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        var firstDigit = number / 10;
        var lastDigit = number % 10;

        var firstPart;
        if (firstDigit == 2) {
            firstPart = "twenty";
        }

        if (firstDigit == 3) {
            firstPart = "thirty";
        }

        if (firstDigit == 4) {
            firstPart = "forty";
        }

        var secondPart = toEnglishNumber(lastDigit);

        return firstPart + "-" + secondPart;
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, we could extract the function for conversion of the first digit to the first english part, such as twenty or thirty:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function convertTens(digit) {
    if (digit == 2) {
        return "twenty";
    }

    if (digit == 3) {
        return "thirty";
    }

    if (digit == 4) {
        return "forty";
    }
}

function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        var firstDigit = number / 10;
        var lastDigit = number % 10;

        var firstPart = convertTens(firstDigit);
        var secondPart = toEnglishNumber(lastDigit);

        return firstPart + "-" + secondPart;
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, it looks like the function <code>convertTens</code> can be simplified through usage of array in the same way as we did before with <code>toEnglishNumber</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var tens = ["", "", "twenty", "thirty", "forty"];

function convertTens(digit) {
    return tens[digit];
}
</code></pre>

<p>At this point, we can write more tests to cover all different first digits, for example fifty-seven, sixty-five, seventy-three, eighty-nine and ninety-one. To make them pass we will have to add corresponding &ldquo;tens&rdquo; number to our array:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var tens = [
    "", "",

    "twenty", "thirty", "forty", "fifty",
    "sixty", "seventy", "eighty", "ninety"
];
</code></pre>

<p>So, that is how we apply three rules of test-driven development. Here is the full code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">describe("toEnglishNumber", function() {

    it("converts 0 to zero", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 0;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "zero";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected);
    });

    it("converts 1 to one", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 1;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "one";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts other one-digit numbers", function() {
        expect(toEnglishNumber(2)).toEqual("two", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(3)).toEqual("three", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(4)).toEqual("four", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(5)).toEqual("five", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(6)).toEqual("six", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(7)).toEqual("seven", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(8)).toEqual("eight", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(9)).toEqual("nine", "english number");
    });

    it("converts 10 to ten", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 10;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "ten";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts other teen numbers", function() {
        expect(toEnglishNumber(11)).toEqual("eleven", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(12)).toEqual("twelve", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(13)).toEqual("thirteen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(14)).toEqual("fourteen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(15)).toEqual("fifteen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(16)).toEqual("sixteen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(17)).toEqual("seventeen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(18)).toEqual("eighteen", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(19)).toEqual("nineteen", "english number");
    });

    it("converts 23 to twenty-three", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 23;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "twenty-three";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts 27 to twenty-seven", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 27;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "twenty-seven";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts 42 to forty-two", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 42;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "forty-two";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts 39 to thirty-nine", function() {
        // ARRANGE
        var number = 39;

        // ACT
        var englishNumber = toEnglishNumber(number);

        // ASSERT
        var expected = "thirty-nine";
        expect(englishNumber).toEqual(expected, "english number");
    });

    it("converts other two-digit numbers", function() {
        expect(toEnglishNumber(57)).toEqual("fifty-seven", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(65)).toEqual("sixty-five", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(73)).toEqual("seventy-three", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(89)).toEqual("eighty-nine", "english number");
        expect(toEnglishNumber(91)).toEqual("ninety-one", "english number");
    });

});

var simpleNumbers = [
    "zero", "one", "two", "three", "four",
    "five", "six", "seven", "eight", "nine",

    "ten", "eleven", "twelve", "thirteen", "fourteen",
    "fifteen", "sixteen", "seventeen", "eighteen", "nineteen"
];

var tens = [
    "", "",

    "twenty", "thirty", "forty", "fifty",
    "sixty", "seventy", "eighty", "ninety"
];

function convertTens(digit) {
    return tens[digit];
}

function toEnglishNumber(number) {
    if (number &gt;= 20) {
        var firstDigit = number / 10;
        var lastDigit = number % 10;

        var firstPart = convertTens(firstDigit);
        var secondPart = toEnglishNumber(lastDigit);

        return firstPart + "-" + secondPart;
    }

    return simpleNumbers[number];
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Exercises</h2>

<ol>
<li>Do you see the missing edge case for two-digit numbers? Write a test for it and make it pass using three rules of test-driven development.</li>
<li>Add support for three-digit numbers.</li>
<li>Add support for negative numbers.</li>
<li>Add support for numbers with the floating point.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Today we have learned a lot of concepts from testing and test-driven development. Also, we have learned the essence of TDD - three rules of TDD. We have learned how to apply these rules on a very simple example. We have touched on how beneficial test-driven development can be when applied well.</p>

<p>In the next article of the series, we will discuss what different kinds of tests exist, how and when to write them and how to apply TDD in these tests. Also, we will get back to our application and implement a new feature.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Test-Driven Development With Javascript: End-to-End Testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/12/23/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-end-to-end-testing/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-23T10:13:33+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/12/23/learning-test-driven-development-with-javascript-end-to-end-testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Level: Beginner.</strong></p>

<p>&ldquo;Learning TDD with Javascript&rdquo; is the series of articles where we learn basics of automated testing and test-driven development. While the language of choice for the code examples is Javascript, all described concepts are language-agnostic and are applicable in various technological stacks. In these articles, a reader is expected to do small exercises after each major topic to reinforce that theoretical knowledge with practice. Some of these exercises are practical and will involve coding, or simple writing; others will be food for thought. Also, a reader might want to get their feedback on these exercises, so don&rsquo;t hesitate to send the results my way: <a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#111;&#108;&#101;&#x6b;&#x73;&#x69;&#105;&#x40;&#116;&#x64;&#100;&#x66;&#101;&#108;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#119;&#46;&#99;&#x6f;&#109;">&#x6f;&#x6c;&#101;&#107;&#x73;&#x69;&#x69;&#64;&#116;&#x64;&#100;&#102;&#x65;&#x6c;&#x6c;&#x6f;&#x77;&#x2e;&#x63;&#111;&#x6d;</a> - feedback on the practice is quite important as it helps to improve quicker, when you know what is well and what can be improved and how. Also, don&rsquo;t hesitate to send any questions and feedback regarding the content of these articles. Your questions, feedback, and your practical results will help authors shape this content better.</p>

<p>Today we are going to learn how to write tests that imitate real user interaction for the whole application. We are going to build a small web application using Vanilla Javascript. Vanilla Javascript is a plain Javascript without any framework or library. Such tests that imitate real user interaction via User Interface (UI) are called End-to-End Tests. These tests are the most simple to write because we only need to think about our application in the same way user does:</p>

<ul>
<li>Imitating the user clicking on the button would mean for us to trigger a button click;</li>
<li>Imitating the user typing text in the input field would mean for us to change input&rsquo;s value;</li>
<li>Imitating the user clicking on the link would mean for us to trigger a link click;</li>
<li>And so on.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>We don&rsquo;t need to think about specific implementation details, such as: which functions and classes do we have in our code and how they interact with each other, is there any interaction with the back-end server or 3rd-party API. Also, we don&rsquo;t need to be proficient with interaction testing - this is the topic for the future series.</p>

<p>Of course, for that kind of simplicity we are trading something off. In the case of End-to-End tests, they are slower, suffer concurrency, wait, and timeout problems, and are harder to maintain in the long run. We don&rsquo;t have to worry about that just yet because we want to learn how to write tests in general, and this kind of simplicity is perfect for us in this case.</p>

<p>Such simplicity stems from the fact that End-to-End tests, mostly, are direct translations of user stories (use case scenarios) into the UI manipulation code.</p>

<h2>User Story</h2>

<p>User stories are scenarios describing an individual feature of the software via user story context, sequences of user interactions and user expectations. User story context is the description of the situation the user and the software system are in at the beginning of the scenario. An example of the system context: &ldquo;user John is registered in the system with password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo;.&rdquo; An example of the user context: &ldquo;user is at the login page.&rdquo; User interaction is the description of a particular action user takes inside of the system, usually, doing something within the UI, for example: &ldquo;User enters email &lsquo;<a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#58;&#x6a;&#111;&#104;&#110;&#x40;&#101;&#x78;&#97;&#x6d;&#112;&#108;&#x65;&#x2e;&#111;&#114;&#103;">&#x6a;&#x6f;&#x68;&#110;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#x61;&#x6d;&#x70;&#108;&#x65;&#46;&#x6f;&#x72;&#103;</a>&rsquo; in the email input field&rdquo; or &ldquo;User clicks on the submit button.&rdquo; Finally, user expectation is the description of what particular information user should receive from the system, for example: &ldquo;User sees the success message on the page&rdquo; or &ldquo;User receives the email with the verification code.&rdquo;</p>

<p>User stories come in different flavor and formats. It can be a free-form text, describing three parts: context, interactions, and expectations; or it can be in a formal &ldquo;Given-When-Then&rdquo; form. &ldquo;Given&rdquo; part is the sequence of the user story context descriptions, &ldquo;When&rdquo; part is the sequence of the user interaction descriptions, and &ldquo;Then&rdquo; part is the sequence of user expectation descriptions. Both forms can be used interchangeably, and some software companies use one or another formal version of the user story format consistently.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example of the free-form user story together with the example of the Given-When-Then user story for the same feature:</p>

<div class="next-table-layout-is-fixed"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Free-form</th>
<th>Given-When-Then</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>User with email &lsquo;<a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#105;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#106;&#x6f;&#x68;&#110;&#64;&#101;&#120;&#x61;&#x6d;&#x70;&#108;&#101;&#46;&#x6f;&#114;&#x67;">&#x6a;&#x6f;&#104;&#110;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#108;&#x65;&#x2e;&#111;&#114;&#x67;</a>&rsquo; and password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; exists in the system<br>John enters his email &lsquo;<a href="&#x6d;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x6a;&#x6f;&#x68;&#x6e;&#x40;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#109;&#x70;&#108;&#101;&#x2e;&#111;&#114;&#x67;">&#x6a;&#111;&#104;&#110;&#x40;&#101;&#x78;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#108;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#114;&#103;</a>&rsquo; into the email field and his password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; into the password field on the login page<br>After that John submits the login form<br>Finally, John expects to see their profile page with the indication of him being logged in (name &lsquo;John&rsquo; is present on the page)</td>
<td><strong>Given</strong> User with email &lsquo;<a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#58;&#x6a;&#x6f;&#104;&#x6e;&#x40;&#101;&#120;&#97;&#x6d;&#112;&#108;&#101;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;">&#106;&#111;&#x68;&#x6e;&#x40;&#x65;&#120;&#x61;&#x6d;&#112;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#x72;&#103;</a>&rsquo; and password &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; exists<br><strong>And</strong> I am at the login page<br><strong>When</strong> I enter &lsquo;<a href="&#x6d;&#x61;&#x69;&#108;&#116;&#x6f;&#58;&#x6a;&#x6f;&#x68;&#x6e;&#64;&#x65;&#120;&#97;&#x6d;&#112;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x2e;&#111;&#x72;&#x67;">&#106;&#x6f;&#104;&#x6e;&#64;&#101;&#120;&#97;&#x6d;&#x70;&#x6c;&#x65;&#x2e;&#x6f;&#x72;&#x67;</a>&rsquo; in the email field<br><strong>And</strong> I enter &lsquo;welcome&rsquo; in the password field<br><strong>And</strong> I click on the submit button<br><strong>Then</strong> I see the profile page<br><strong>And</strong> I see my name as the title of the profile page</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>As we can see, free-form can be very vague and is very flexible, and formal form is more strict and precise. The free-form on its own doesn&rsquo;t have much upsides or downsides - it is as good as it is written. On the other hand, the formal form does give us some value and also trades something off for that value. They are generally easy to write and, because they are so specific, are easy to translate to the automated test. On the other hand, they may hamper creativity either while creating the user story or when implementing it.</p>

<p>It is important to mention that these use case scenarios are not full user stories or features. One feature can have multiple scenarios like that - together they are called acceptance criteria. When all such scenarios of the given feature work correctly, the feature is done. There is another vital part of the user story - general description, that should contain the rationale behind the story and the value for the user or any other important actor in the system, such as the stakeholder. Before we write scenarios, we often come up with the rationale like that and it drives us to write a scenario. For example, for the feature above we would have used something like that:</p>

<div class="next-table-layout-is-fixed"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Free-form</th>
<th>Given-When-Then</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>John needs to authenticate to the system so that he can access his private content</td>
<td><strong>As John</strong>, I want to be able to authenticate to the system<br><strong>So that</strong> I can access my private content</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Because formal form user stories are more precise, easier to write and simpler to translate to the automated test, we are going to use them to learn End-to-End testing in the context of Test-Driven Development.</p>

<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write a scenario for authentication story, when John enters the wrong password.</li>
<li>Write a user story with rationale and scenarios for the sign-up feature.</li>
<li>Imagine we are developing an instant messaging application. What do you think would be the next feature after login/sign-up? Write the user story with rationale and scenarios for this feature.</li>
</ol>


<p>Do you have questions? Or do you want to get quick feedback on how you did the exercises? - mail me: <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#116;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x6f;&#x6c;&#101;&#107;&#x73;&#x69;&#x69;&#64;&#x74;&#100;&#100;&#102;&#101;&#108;&#108;&#111;&#x77;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;">&#x6f;&#108;&#101;&#x6b;&#115;&#105;&#105;&#64;&#x74;&#x64;&#100;&#x66;&#101;&#108;&#108;&#x6f;&#119;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#109;</a></p>

<h2>Setting Up the Project</h2>

<p>Now we will be writing a simple web application, using Vanilla Javascript (ECMAScript 5), so that our setup is rather simple. For the testing, we will be using a standalone version of the Jasmine testing framework. Also, we will be writing a single page application (SPA), so that we don&rsquo;t have to worry about rendering different pages in our tests for now. We are aiming for the following directory structure of our project:</p>

<pre><code>.
├── lib
├───── .. external libraries, such as Jasmine ..
├── spec
├───── .. sources with Jasmine automated tests ..
└── src
├───── .. sources with our main code ..
├── index.html       - entry point to the application
├── SpecRunner.html  - entry point to our test suite
</code></pre>

<p>First, create required directories: <code>lib</code>, <code>spec</code> and <code>src</code>. Then download the latest standalone Jasmine release here: <a href="https://github.com/jasmine/jasmine/releases">https://github.com/jasmine/jasmine/releases</a> (jasmine-standalone-{version}.zip file). At the time of writing, the version is <code>2.5.2</code>. Unzip that file into your project directory. You should get the following files from it:</p>

<ul>
<li><code>./lib/jasmine-2.5.2/</code> directory - contains all the resources required by Jasmine.</li>
<li><code>./SpecRunner.html</code> - example entry point to our test suite.</li>
<li><code>./src/Player.js</code> and <code>./src/Song.js</code> - example source files.</li>
<li><code>./spec/PlayerSpec.js</code> and <code>./spec/SpecHelper.js</code> - example automated Jasmine tests.</li>
</ul>


<p>Now, try to open <code>SpecRunner.html</code> in your browser. It should run these example tests, and they should all pass. Here is how it should look like:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-example-run.png" alt="Jasmine example test run with all tests green" /></p>

<p>Also, create an empty <code>index.html</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html lang="en"&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="UTF-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Title&lt;/title&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>And now we should have the desired project structure. So how does that Jasmine testing framework works, anyways?</p>

<h2>Crash Course into Jasmine</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s take a look at the example test file to get the gist of how Jasmine works:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/PlayerSpec.js

describe("Player", function() {
  var player;
  var song;

  beforeEach(function() {
    player = new Player();
    song = new Song();
  });

  it("should be able to play a Song", function() {
    player.play(song);
    expect(player.currentlyPlayingSong).toEqual(song);

    //demonstrates use of custom matcher
    expect(player).toBePlaying(song);
  });

  describe("when song has been paused", function() {
    beforeEach(function() {
      player.play(song);
      player.pause();
    });

    it("should indicate that the song is currently paused", function() {
      expect(player.isPlaying).toBeFalsy();

      // demonstrates use of 'not' with a custom matcher
      expect(player).not.toBePlaying(song);
    });

    it("should be possible to resume", function() {
      player.resume();
      expect(player.isPlaying).toBeTruthy();
      expect(player.currentlyPlayingSong).toEqual(song);
    });
  });

  // demonstrates use of spies to intercept and test method calls
  it("tells the current song if the user has made it a favorite", function() {
    spyOn(song, 'persistFavoriteStatus');

    player.play(song);
    player.makeFavorite();

    expect(song.persistFavoriteStatus).toHaveBeenCalledWith(true);
  });

  //demonstrates use of expected exceptions
  describe("#resume", function() {
    it("should throw an exception if song is already playing", function() {
      player.play(song);

      expect(function() {
        player.resume();
      }).toThrowError("song is already playing");
    });
  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>First important concept here is the <code>describe("...", function () { ... })</code>. <code>describe</code> function is used to describe a certain concept or a certain context. For example, <code>describe("Player", ...)</code> means that we are going to define tests for <code>Player</code> class or some other <code>Player</code> concept. Also, describes can be nested to indicate that we are describing some specific context (<code>describe("when a song has been paused", ...)</code>) or sub-concept of current concept, such as the method of currently described class (<code>describe("#resume", ...)</code>). That is a good example, of what the unit test suite might be describing. In the case of End-to-End tests we would like to describe a full feature, so <code>describe("Login Feature", ...)</code> is a good bet. The second argument for the <code>describe</code> is the function that will contain all tests and sub-describes for the described concept. This function is the capturing closure, so defining variables and functions on the outer-level describe will make them available on the inner-level describes and the tests themselves.</p>

<p>Second important concept here is the <code>it("...", function () { ... })</code>. <code>it</code> function is used to create a test for the currently described concept, context or sub-concept. The first argument is the description of what <em>it</em> does, where <em>it</em> is the described concept. For example, given we describe a <code>music player</code> and our context is <code>when the volume is at max</code>, then we might write the test <code>it("is deafening", ...)</code>. In the case of End-to-End tests we are describing a feature, so <em>it</em> will refer to our application, or application&rsquo;s user interface, for example: <code>it("shows user's nickname", ...)</code>. The second argument to the <code>it</code> is the function with the test itself. Here we will setup the stage for the test, call our main code and verify that everything happened as we expect.</p>

<p>Finally, the third important concept is the <code>expect(...).to...</code>. That is Jasmine&rsquo;s form of assertion. That is where we verify that our code worked as we expect it to. As an argument to expect we provide an actual value. The actual value is something that our code has returned as a result of the function or method execution or something that we have read from the UI using UI manipulation code, or something that we have read from some 3rd party service, such as our back-end server, 3rd-party API or database. Essentially, this is the value that we are verifying to be correct. The second part is the Jasmine matcher - the method defined on the object, that is returned from <code>expect(value)</code> call, that allows us to define what we want to assert about that value. The most used one is <code>toEqual(...)</code>, which asserts that the value was equal to some expected value.</p>

<p>These three concepts should be enough to start writing tests. Don&rsquo;t worry about everything else that you see in this example file from standalone Jasmine distribution. We will discover some of these concepts as we go. Now, let&rsquo;s remove <code>src/Player.js</code>, <code>src/Song.js</code>, <code>spec/PlayerSpec.js</code> and <code>spec/SpecHelper.js</code>, and run our test suite - it is enough to reload the page to re-run our test suite. Test run should report that <code>No specs found</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-no-specs-found.png" alt="Jasmine no specs found example" /></p>

<p>To get the gist of how <code>describe("...", function () { ... })</code>, <code>it("...", function () { ... })</code> and <code>expect(...).toEqual(...)</code> works, let&rsquo;s write our first failing test. Also, that will let us see if the testing framework is configured correctly and is capable of showing us the test failure. Let&rsquo;s create a new file called <code>spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js

describe("testing framework", function () {
  it("works", function () {
    expect(2 + 2).toEqual(5);
  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>And we need to add this test file to the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>:</p>

<p>&#8220;`html</p>

<!-- include source files here... -->




<!-- include spec files here... -->


<script src="spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js"></script>


<pre><code>
And if we run our test suite, we should see a failure:
</code></pre>

<p>testing framework works
  Expected 4 to equal 5.
&#8220;`</p>

<p>And we ought to make it pass by fixing our incorrect assertion: <code>expect(2 + 2).toEqual(4);</code>. And if we run the test suite again, by reloading the page in the browser, all the test should pass.</p>

<h2>Writing our First Simple Tests</h2>

<p>Now we can write some real tests to practice usage of <code>describe</code>, <code>it</code> and <code>expect(...).toEqual</code>: let&rsquo;s create <code>ArithmeticsSpec.js</code> and write some tests for behavior of <code>add</code> function:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js

describe("Arithmetics", function () {

  describe("#add(a, b)", function () {
    it("calculates the sum of two numbers", function () {
      // ARRANGE
      var a = 3;
      var b = 4;
      var expected = 7;

      // ACT
      var actual = Arithmetics.add(a, b);

      // ASSERT
      expect(actual).toEqual(expected);
    });
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t forget to add the <code>&lt;script src="spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;</code> to the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. This test will fail first because <code>Arithmetics</code> module is not defined. We will define it as an empty object. Next failure is because <code>Arithmetics.add</code> is not a function - it is undefined. We will define that function with two arguments inside of the <code>Arithmetics</code> object. Finally, the test will fail, because we expect the result to be seven, but it was undefined. We will make the simplest thing we can do to pass the failing test - return seven. That will make the test pass. The code will be in <code>src/Arithmetics.js</code>, which we include in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>, and will look like that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/Arithmetics.js

var Arithmetics = {
  add: function (a, b) {
    return 7;
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>That, of course, is not correct implementation, so we need another test to drive out the proper implementation - test with different inputs and a different result. To make it pass we will have to use <code>a + b</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js
describe("Arithmetics", function () {

  describe("#add(a, b)", function () {
    it("calculates the sum of two numbers", function () { ... });

    it("calculates the sum of two other numbers", function () {
      // ARRANGE
      var a = 73;
      var b = 89;
      var expected = 162;

      // ACT
      var actual = Arithmetics.add(a, b);

      // ASSERT
      expect(actual).toEqual(expected);
    });
  });

});

// src/Arithmetics.js
var Arithmetics = {
  add: function (a, b) {
    return a + b;
  }
};
</code></pre>

<h3>Three &ldquo;A&#8221;s: Arrange, Act, and Assert</h3>

<p>Have you noticed three comments that I have left in the example tests&#8217; code: <code>ARRANGE</code>, <code>ACT</code> and <code>ASSERT</code>? These are three &ldquo;A&#8221;s of writing a good test. Arrange is the part of the test, where we set up the stage: prepare input data, create objects, load resources, change the state of the system - it is the part where we create the context for our test. Act is the part of the test, where we call our system under the test. In the <code>Arithmetics</code> example it was a function <code>Arithmetics.add(a, b)</code>. The system under the test can return some useful value or change its state. To verify that either is correct we, finally, use Assert section of our test - part of the test where we verify the outcome of the call to the system under the test.</p>

<p>The sections <code>ARRANGE</code>, <code>ACT</code> and <code>ASSERT</code> are spelled out in the comments only for the reader&rsquo;s convenience - usually, real projects don&rsquo;t have such comments. It is worth noting that for learning and practicing purposes it is a good idea to name these sections explicitly in our tests - this develops a habit of recognizing which part of the test should belong to which section. Also, the formula Act -> Arrange -> Assert makes it easier to come up with the test when we lack deep experience in testing, or with the particular testing framework, or an environment.</p>

<p>Going a bit back to our user story scenarios: have you noticed the connection between &ldquo;Arrange, Act and Assert&rdquo; and &ldquo;Given-When-Then&rdquo;? Arrange part of the test corresponds to the Given part of the scenario, Act part of the test corresponds to the When part of the scenario, and Assert part of the test corresponds to the Then part of the scenario. Let&rsquo;s see it on of our previous example scenarios:</p>

<div class="next-table-is-top-aligned"></div>


<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Test Section</th>
<th>Scenario Step</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><hr></td>
<td><hr></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ARRANGE</td>
<td><strong>Given</strong> User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists<br><strong>And</strong> I am at the login page</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><br></td>
<td><br></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ACT</td>
<td><strong>When</strong> I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field<br><strong>And</strong> I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field<br><strong>And</strong> I click on the submit button</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td><br></td>
<td><br></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>ASSERT</td>
<td><strong>Then</strong> I see the profile page<br><strong>And</strong> I see my name as the title of the profile page</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Write tests and implement functions on <code>Arithmetics</code> module: <code>subtract</code>, <code>multiply</code> and <code>divide</code>.</li>
<li>Inline Arrange, Act and Assert in a one-liner. Can you still recognize implicit Arrange, Act and Assert sections in that one line? Is it more or less readable? Is there a middle ground between two versions? Why would you choose one or the other?</li>
<li>Classify parts of the free-form story for the user log in from before as Arrange, Act, and Assert. Was it easier, than classifying formal Given-When-Then form? Was it harder? Or maybe the same? How would it be if you never saw Given-When-Then version of that free-form story?</li>
</ol>


<h2>Writing our First End-to-End Test</h2>

<p>Now that we know approximately, how to arrange the steps of our scenario into the test, let&rsquo;s give it a shot. We will start by creating a new test file for our login feature called <code>LoginFeatureSpec.js</code>. Don&rsquo;t forget to put an appropriate script tag in the <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. We will start by writing the skeleton of our test suite: <code>describe</code> and <code>it</code> inside of it. Next, we will put scenario steps as comments to our test, and we will split them into three sections: Arrange, Act, and Assert. It will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js

describe("Login Feature", function () {

  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE
    // Given User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists
    // And I am at the login page

    // ACT
    // When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field
    // And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field
    // And I click on the submit button

    // ASSERT
    // Then I see the profile page
    // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>Next step would be to change the first <strong>Given</strong> comment to the function call. We should give a good readable name to that function. One straightforward option would be <code>givenUserExists(email, password).</code> Another good option is <code>addUser({email: email, password: password})</code>. While they are not that different, I prefer <code>addUser</code> for its higher conceptual flexibility - we will likely need that function in some different scenario step in the future. While I prefer that, we should not do that yet, because we might never need the function like that, and <code>givenUserExists</code> will do us more good right now since it resembles the scenario step so much. When we need this flexibility, we&rsquo;ll perform a refactoring. So for now, let&rsquo;s create an empty function with that name in a new file <code>spec/FeatureSteps.js</code> and load this file from our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>.</p>

<p>This empty function, on its own, doesn&rsquo;t do us much good because all our tests will pass. If we continue replacing our steps in comments with such functions, we will end up with one big failure at the Assert section, and we will have to write a lot of code at once to fix that. To drive ourselves to implement the function <code>givenUserExists</code> properly right now, we should write an assertion right after the call. This assertion is not part of Assert section - it is a part of test-driving the functionality of our feature steps. A good assertion here will be to ask our user storage mechanism if such user exists right after we created that user. Also, it would be a good idea to check that user does not exist, before we created it. Also, we will extract variables <code>email</code> and <code>password</code> because we have to repeat them all over the place already. Let&rsquo;s see how it will look like:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js

describe("Login Feature", function () {

  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE

    // Given User with email ‘john@example.org’ and password ‘welcome’ exists
    var email = "john@example.org";
    var password = "welcome";
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);
    givenUserExists(email, password);
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);

    // ...
  });

});
</code></pre>

<p>When we run our tests, the breadcrumbs of test failures will drive us to create this basic functionality. First, we will create <code>Users.js</code> with empty <code>Users</code> module and import it from <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. Then, next failure will drive us to add method <code>exists(email, password)</code> on <code>Users</code> module, that will always return <code>false</code>. Next, make function <code>givenUserExists(email, password)</code> call <code>Users.add(email, password)</code>, which in turn will make us create a function <code>Users.add(email, password)</code>, that will store email-password pair to the list of users in the memory. And, finally, make <code>Users.exists</code> to search for the email-password pair in that in-memory list. And finally, our test will pass. Let&rsquo;s take a look at how these steps will look in our code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// =&gt; Error: Users is undefined
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {};

// =&gt; Error: Users.exists is not a function
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  exists: function (email, password) {}
};

// =&gt; Error: expected undefined to equal false
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  exists: function (email, password) {
    return false;
  }
};

// =&gt; Error: expected false to equal true
// in the (second assertion)
// in spec/FeatureSteps.js:
function givenUserExists(email, password) {
  Users.add(email, password);
}

// =&gt; Error: Users.add is not a function
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  users: [],

  exists: function (email, password) { ... },

  add: function (email, password) {
    this.users.push({email: email, password: password});
  }
}

// this still fails with:
// =&gt; Error: expected false to equal true
// because we need to implement Users.exists "properly"
// in src/Users.js:
var Users = {
  users: [],

  exists: function (email, password) {
    return this.users.length &gt; 0;
  },

  add: function (email, password) { ... }
}

// =&gt; All tests PASS
</code></pre>

<p>It is funny, how simple <code>Users.exists(email, password)</code> function is. It verifies that we have at least one user. While this is not a correct code, this is good enough for our current test. As we know that this code is not entirely correct, we need to remember to write the test(s) to prove it incorrect, so that we can make it proper with confidence. Since we want first to finish the current test, we should add a to-do list item to write such test. We have two edge cases here that will not work with our implementation: when we have only one user in the system and the credentials we provided do not match and when we have multiple users in the system, and we provide correct credentials for the second one:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">xdescribe("when user has different credentials", function () {
  it("does not allow to login with wrong credentials", function () {

  });
});

xdescribe("when there are more than one user", function () {
  it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {

  });
});
</code></pre>

<p>Have you noticed <code>xdescribe</code>? It is a different form of the <code>describe</code>, that allows us to mark the whole context as pending. It won&rsquo;t run the tests inside, and it will mark them as pending in the test run report. That is the ultimate way to maintain a Test-Driven TODO List. As we test-drive our code, we will find more of these. In the report they look like this:</p>

<p><img src="/images/learning-tdd-with-js/jasmine-e2e-pending-tests.png" alt="pending jasmine tests" /></p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s finish continue implementing our steps. The comment <code>And I am at the login page</code> transparently becomes a function <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code>. As we already have seen, it doesn&rsquo;t do us any good just to replace the comment with a function call that does nothing - so we should surround it with proper assertions. We know that login page should have some text input for email and another password field for password, and we will need a button to confirm user&rsquo;s intent to log in. Also, because we are developing a single page application, we would need some container for the currently active page. Let&rsquo;s say we need these things:</p>

<ul>
<li>Initially, we will have only one container with <code>id="page"</code> and no content. We probably ought to define it in our HTML file.</li>
<li>When we render our login page, we should have:

<ul>
<li>email text input field with <code>id="email"</code>,</li>
<li>password input field with <code>id="password"</code>,</li>
<li>and button with <code>id="do_login"</code>.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Now that we have spelt this out, it is fairly straightforward to write assertions surrounding the <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code> call:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// Initially, we will have only one container with `id="page"`
var container = document.querySelector("#page");
expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
// and no content
expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");
</code></pre>

<p>That fails because we don&rsquo;t have such element in our HTML. We need to create it both in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. Also, now it will be important to move all our <code>&lt;script&gt;</code> tags from the <code>&lt;head&gt;</code> to the <code>&lt;body&gt;</code> below the container that we have just created. <code>SpecRunner.html</code> should look this way after that:</p>

<pre><code class="html">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;
&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;meta charset="utf-8"&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;Jasmine Spec Runner v2.5.2&lt;/title&gt;

    &lt;link rel="shortcut icon" type="image/png" href="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine_favicon.png"&gt;
    &lt;link rel="stylesheet" href="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine.css"&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;

&lt;body&gt;

    &lt;div id="page"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/jasmine-html.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="lib/jasmine-2.5.2/boot.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;!-- include source files here... --&gt;
    &lt;script src="src/Arithmetics.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="src/Users.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

    &lt;!-- include spec files here... --&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/JasmineWorksSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/ArithmeticsSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/FeatureSteps.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
    &lt;script src="spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Now, our next failure is that <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage()</code> function is not defined. We can define it as empty function in our <code>spec/FeatureSteps.js</code> file for now. This will turn our tests green again. We still haven&rsquo;t made our assertions about the state of the UI after the call to <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code> - let&rsquo;s do this now:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("input");
expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");
</code></pre>

<p>That fails with the error <code>Cannot read property tagName of null</code>, which means that we don&rsquo;t have <code>#email</code> element inside of the <code>#page</code> container. Simplest thing to do would be to add that element to the <code>#page</code> container in our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. And it won&rsquo;t work! Because we have an assertion that verifies, that before calling to the <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code> we do not have anything in the <code>#page</code> container. Now we have to do something useful in the function <code>givenIAmAtTheLoginPage</code>. For example, we can call <code>LoginPage.render()</code>. Which does not exist yet and we will need to create it in the file <code>src/LoginPage.js</code> and load it from our <code>SpecRunner.html</code>. To fix current failure we will need to create a <code>#email</code> element there and append it to our <code>#page</code> container:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
  LoginPage.render();
}

// src/LoginPage.js
var LoginPage = {
  render: function () {
    var emailInput = document.createElement("div");
    emailInput.id = "email";

    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    container.appendChild(emailInput);
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>That makes the current test failure go away, but we have two more: <code>Expected 'DIV' to equal 'input'.</code> and <code>Expected undefined to equal 'email'.</code>. To make these pass, we would need to change <code>document.createElement(...)</code> call to use <code>input</code> tag name and also we will need to set the input type to <code>email</code>. And as we see, the tag name stored in <code>emailInput.tagName</code> is all-caps, so we will have to fix our assertion also to expect that:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// first we'll fix the assertion:
// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");

// and then we will fix the emailInput creation:
// in src/LoginPage.js
var emailInput = document.createElement("input");
emailInput.id = "email";
emailInput.type = "email";
</code></pre>

<p>And if we run our tests, they all pass. Great! We should now do the same for our password input field and the login button:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");
var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");

// in src/LoginPage.js
var passwordInput = document.createElement("input");
passwordInput.id = "password";
passwordInput.type = "password";
container.appendChild(passwordInput);

var loginButton = document.createElement("button");
loginButton.id = "do_login";
loginButton.textContent = "Login";
container.appendChild(loginButton);
</code></pre>

<p>And all tests pass again. Let&rsquo;s take another look at how our test looks like. It is quite complicated, and it has so much stuff, that is hugely detailed and precise, that it is not possible to see a user story scenario there anymore. One possible solution to that problem is to push the assertions that are related to the feature scenario step to the respective step functions. Now it looks much better. We should use the same concept for all our further steps. After refactoring test code looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
  // ARRANGE
  var email = "john@example.org";
  var password = "welcome";
  givenUserExists(email, password);
  givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

  // ACT
  // When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field
  // And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field
  // And I click on the submit button

  // ASSERT
  // Then I see the profile page
  // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
});

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password) {
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

    Users.add(email, password);

    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);
}

function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");

    LoginPage.render();

    var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
    expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");

    var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
    expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");

    var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
    expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
    expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s follow the same pattern for our Act section. First, we will deal with <code>When I enter ‘john@example.org’ in the email field</code>. This seems to be a call to a function <code>whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email)</code> - we will implement it using Javascript&rsquo;s APIs. We will do the same for the <code>And I enter ‘welcome’ in the password field</code>, which will use the same function <code>whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password).</code> Finally, we will implement <code>whenIClickOn("#do_login")</code> as a replacement for the comment <code>And I click on the submit button</code>. We will also sprinkle assertions inside of the steps to make sure that we are using the Javascript APIs correctly. The code will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
    // ARRANGE
    var email = "john@example.org";
    var password = "welcome";
    givenUserExists(email, password);
    givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

    // ACT
    whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email);
    whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password);
    whenIClickOn("#do_login");

    // ASSERT
    // Then I see the profile page
    // And I see my name as the title of the profile page
});

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function whenIEnterInTheField(selector, value) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(element.value).toEqual("");

    element.value = value;

    var elementAfterChange = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.value).toEqual(value);
}

function whenIClickOn(selector) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);

    element.click();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now comes the most interesting part of writing this feature test - Assert section. So far, Arrange and Act sections were driving us to create an infrastructure-like code of our application. Now, with Assert section we will have to implement more of our domain logic. Let&rsquo;s start with the <code>Then I see the profile page</code>. Let&rsquo;s try to figure our what that could mean:</p>

<ul>
<li>We no longer have a login page in our <code>#page</code> container.</li>
<li><code>#page</code> container should somehow indicate that we are on the <code>Profile</code> page:

<ul>
<li>could be achieved by adding a sub-container with <code>id="profile_page"</code> to it.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>We don&rsquo;t know much more about what the profile page is. What we do know is:

<ul>
<li>the profile page has a name of the user as the title of the page.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Interesting, so far, we didn&rsquo;t have a concept of the Name of the User. I guess it is time to create one in our arrange block, with all the changes and additional assertions in our feature steps that we have to do:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
// ARRANGE
var email = "john@example.org";
var password = "welcome";
var name = "John Smith";
givenUserExists(email, password, name);

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password, name) {
  expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

  Users.add(email, password, name);            // &lt;=

  expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);

  expect(Users.nameOf(email)).toEqual(name);   // &lt;=
}

// also we need to add name field to the user data
// and implement nameOf(email) function
// in src/Users.js
add: function (email, password, name) {
  this.users.push({
    email: email,
    password: password,
    name: name
  });
},

nameOf: function (email) {
  return this.users[0].name;
}
</code></pre>

<p>And the tests will pass again. And now we have a tested concept of the name in our code. Tested - to the extent required for this test, where we have only one user in the system. Now we can replace the comment <code>Then I see the profile page</code> with the scenario step function call <code>thenISeeTheProfilePage()</code>. The implementation of it will verify that <code>#email</code>, <code>#password</code> and <code>#do_login</code> are no longer present on the page and it will verify that container <code>#page-profile</code> is present and it has <code>#title</code> element in it. Making it pass will require us to add a <code>click</code> event listener to the <code>loginButton</code> in the <code>LoginPage</code>, that will remove contents of the <code>#page</code> container and will call to <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> following the analogy of <code>LoginPage</code>. That drives us to create this module and its <code>render()</code> function. According to our next test failure, this function should create <code>#profile_page</code> sub-container in <code>#page</code> container, so we do that. Finally, we have one last failure, that drives us to create <code>#title</code> element in <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> function. And all tests are green again. Let&rsquo;s take a look at these changes:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
// ASSERT
// Then I see the profile page
thenISeeTheProfilePage();

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function thenISeeTheProfilePage() {
  // assert login page is gone
  expect(document.querySelector("#email")).toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#password")).toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#do_login")).toEqual(null);

  // assert profile page is present
  expect(document.querySelector("#page #profile_page")).not.toEqual(null);
  expect(document.querySelector("#profile_page #title")).not.toEqual(null);
}

// in src/LoginPage.js at the end of render() function:
render: function() {
  // ...

  loginButton.addEventListener("click", LoginPage.onLogin);
},

onLogin: function () {
  container.innerHTML = "";
  ProfilePage.render();
}

// in src/ProfilePage.js
var ProfilePage = {
  render: function () {
    var profileContainer = document.createElement("div");
    profileContainer.id = "profile_page";
    container.appendChild(profileContainer);

    var title = document.createElement("h1");
    title.id = "title";
    profileContainer.appendChild(title);
  }
};
</code></pre>

<p>At last, we can implement the last step - <code>And I see my name as the title of the profile page</code>. A good guess for the step name would be <code>thenISeeTextAt("#title", name)</code>. The function will simply select element <code>#title</code> and verify its <code>element.textContent</code>. As expected, it fails with the error <code>Expected '' to equal 'John Smith'</code> and we should fix that within the <code>ProfilePage.render()</code> function by assigning <code>title.textContent</code> to the <code>Users.currentUser().name</code>. This fails because we didn&rsquo;t define <code>Users.currentUser()</code> function and this is simple to do for our current test - just return the first user. After that all our tests pass. The code will look like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
thenISeeTextAt("#title", name);

// in spec/FeatureSteps.js
function thenISeeTextAt(selector, text) {
  var element = document.querySelector(selector);
  expect(element.textContent).toEqual(text);
}

// in src/ProfilePage.js
title.textContent = Users.currentUser().name;

// in src/Users.js
currentUser: function () {
    return this.users[0];
}
</code></pre>

<p>We have finally, implemented our first feature test. That was quite some work. Also, the functionality of <code>Users</code> module is way incomplete - we need to write more tests to cover different cases. That is how our test code and production code looks like:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/LoginFeatureSpec.js
describe("Login Feature", function () {

    it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {
        // ARRANGE
        var email = "john@example.org";
        var password = "welcome";
        var name = "John Smith";
        givenUserExists(email, password, name);
        givenIAmAtTheLoginPage();

        // ACT
        whenIEnterInTheField("#email", email);
        whenIEnterInTheField("#password", password);
        whenIClickOn("#do_login");

        // ASSERT
        thenISeeTheProfilePage();
        thenISeeTextAt("#title", name);
    });

    xdescribe("when user has different credentials", function () {
        it("does not allow to login with wrong credentials", function () {

        });
    });

    xdescribe("when there are more than one user", function () {
        it("allows to login with correct credentials", function () {

        });
    });

});
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// spec/FeatureSteps.js
function givenUserExists(email, password, name) {
    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(false);

    Users.add(email, password, name);

    expect(Users.exists(email, password)).toEqual(true);
    expect(Users.nameOf(email)).toEqual(name);
}

function givenIAmAtTheLoginPage() {
    var container = document.querySelector("#page");
    expect(container).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(container.innerHTML).toEqual("");

    LoginPage.render();

    var emailInput = container.querySelector("#email");
    expect(emailInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(emailInput.type).toEqual("email");

    var passwordInput = container.querySelector("#password");
    expect(passwordInput.tagName).toEqual("INPUT");
    expect(passwordInput.type).toEqual("password");

    var loginButton = container.querySelector("#do_login");
    expect(loginButton.tagName).toEqual("BUTTON");
    expect(loginButton.textContent).toEqual("Login");
}

function whenIEnterInTheField(selector, value) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(element.value).toEqual("");

    element.value = value;

    var elementAfterChange = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.value).toEqual(value);
}

function whenIClickOn(selector) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element).not.toEqual(null);

    element.click();
}

function thenISeeTheProfilePage() {
    // assert login page is gone
    expect(document.querySelector("#email")).toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#password")).toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#do_login")).toEqual(null);

    // assert profile page is present
    expect(document.querySelector("#page #profile_page")).not.toEqual(null);
    expect(document.querySelector("#profile_page #title")).not.toEqual(null);
}

function thenISeeTextAt(selector, text) {
    var element = document.querySelector(selector);
    expect(element.textContent).toEqual(text);
}
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/Users.js
var Users = {
    users: [],

    exists: function (email, password) {
        return this.users.length &gt; 0;
    },

    add: function (email, password, name) {
        this.users.push({
            email: email,
            password: password,
            name: name
        });
    },

    nameOf: function (email) {
        return this.users[0].name;
    },

    currentUser: function () {
        return this.users[0];
    }
};
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/LoginPage.js
var container = document.querySelector("#page");

var LoginPage = {
    render: function () {
        var emailInput = document.createElement("input");
        emailInput.id = "email";
        emailInput.type = "email";
        container.appendChild(emailInput);

        var passwordInput = document.createElement("input");
        passwordInput.id = "password";
        passwordInput.type = "password";
        container.appendChild(passwordInput);

        var loginButton = document.createElement("button");
        loginButton.id = "do_login";
        loginButton.textContent = "Login";
        container.appendChild(loginButton);

        loginButton.addEventListener("click", LoginPage.onLogin);
    },

    onLogin: function () {
        container.innerHTML = "";
        ProfilePage.render();
    }
};
</code></pre>

<pre><code class="javascript">// src/ProfilePage.js
var ProfilePage = {
    render: function () {
        var profileContainer = document.createElement("div");
        profileContainer.id = "profile_page";
        container.appendChild(profileContainer);

        var title = document.createElement("h1");
        title.id = "title";
        title.textContent = Users.currentUser().name;
        profileContainer.appendChild(title);
    }
};
</code></pre>

<p>Now we could add <code>&lt;div id="page"&gt;</code> to our <code>index.html</code>, and load our <code>src/*</code> scripts after it, and add <code>&lt;script&gt;Users.add("john@example.org", "welcome", "John Smith"); LoginPage.render();&lt;/script&gt;</code> at the end to start our application. Enjoy the application that implements one happy path of our feature (we still have quite a few different paths to cover). Also, it might be a good idea to style the application slightly better, than plain inputs and buttons, but we are not going to cover that in these series. This single feature test takes a lot of time to write because it is the first feature test in the empty application. Essentially, it has driven a lot of different architectural decisions, which don&rsquo;t necessary need to be done the way they were done in this article. Writing a second test for the same feature is much easier and third one, and all consecutive are also easier.</p>

<h3>Exercises</h3>

<ol>
<li>Remove <code>x</code> prefix from the <code>xdescribe</code> tests and implement them using techniques described in this article - write a user story scenario, translate it to the test code and make sure to fix all the test failures one feature step at a time.</li>
<li>Discover more interesting edge cases. Make the tests for them and make them all pass.</li>
<li>Write sign-up feature&rsquo;s user story and implement it with feature tests.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Bottom Line</h2>

<p>Today we have learned how to write tests for the whole application that imitate real user interaction. We have seen how, test-driving the functionality can help discovering new user story scenarios. Essentially, every time we write simple, but not so correct code that makes our test pass, we need to think what would be the scenario to prove that code wrong and add that scenario on our to-do list, which is represented by pending tests, which have only their descriptions.</p>

<p>In the next article of the series, we will dig deeper on what exactly we did today, what it means to Test-Drive the code, what are the laws, rules, tips and tricks of Test-Driven Development. Next article of the series assumes, that login and sign-up features are fully test-driven and implemented. We will be implementing a brand new feature of our application.</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Your Own Testing Framework. Part 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/11/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-5/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-13T12:50:51+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/11/13/build-your-own-testing-framework-part-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome back to the new issue of &ldquo;Build Your Own Testing Framework&rdquo; series! Did you notice, that out testing framework quits on the first failure? It probably should run all tests, collect all failures and present them nicely. This is what we are going to accomplish today:</p>

<ul>
<li>Make sure all tests run even when there is a failure.</li>
<li>Make sure exit code is correct.</li>
</ul>


<!-- more -->


<p>This article is the fifth one of the series “Build Your Own Testing Framework” so make sure to stick around for next parts! Find all posts of these series can <a href="/blog/categories/build-your-own-testing-framework/">here</a>.</p>

<p>Shall we get started?</p>

<h2>Catch and report a test failure</h2>

<p>Our test suite should no longer bubble up any exceptions. We can achieve that by making an appropriate assertion. And also we should verify that other tests execute after the failure:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function FailureTest(t) {
    this.testItDoesNotBubbleUpExceptions = function () {
        var aSpy = t.spy();

        t.assertNotThrow(function () {
            runTestSuite(function (t) {
                this.testFailure = function () {
                    t.assertTrue(false);
                };

                this.testSomething = aSpy;
            });
        });

        aSpy.assertCalled();
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>As expected, this fails with an appropriate error <code>Error: Expected not to throw error, but thrown 'Expected to be true, but got false'</code> indicating that we are bubbling up all errors at the moment. Also, notice how the execution of the whole test suite stops at that point, and it just exits the program with error code <code>1</code>. A simple <code>try .. catch</code> block will fix the issue:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">// in runTestSuite function
    for (var testName in testSuitePrototype) {
        if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
            reporter.reportTest(testName);
            var testSuite = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

            try {
                testSuite[testName]();
            } catch (error) {
                // do nothing, for now
            }
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>All tests now run successfully. This code is starting to become unreadable, so it is a good point to refactor. We will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Extract whole <code>try .. catch</code> as a function <code>runTest</code>. Its current responsibility is only to run the test and ignore any failure;</li>
<li>Extract contents of <code>if</code> statement that matches the test name as a function <code>handleTest</code>. Its responsibility is to report the test, create a fresh testSuite and kick off <code>runTest</code>;</li>
<li>Extract the whole <code>for</code> statement as <code>runAllTests</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>Here is the final snippet of code:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
    try {
        testSuite[testName]();
    } catch (error) {
        // do nothing, for now
    }
}

function handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor) {
    reporter.reportTest(testName);
    runTest(createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor), testName);
}

function runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor) {
    for (var testName in testSuitePrototype) {
        if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
            handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor);
        }
    }
}

function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    options = options || {};
    var reporter = options.reporter || new SimpleReporter();

    var testSuitePrototype = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

    reporter.reportTestSuite(
        getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
    );

    runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor);
}
</code></pre>

<h2>Exit with code 1</h2>

<p>Now, when at least one test fails in a suite of tests, the whole suite should fail (after running the rest of its tests). And the indicator of such failure should be an exit code of the process. Let&rsquo;s write a test:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function FailureTest(t) {
    // ...

    this.testItExitsWithProcessCodeOne = function () {
        var processSpy = new ProcessSpy();

        runTestSuite(function (t) {
            this.testFailure = function () {
                t.assertTrue(false);
            };
        }, {process: processSpy});

        t.assertEqual(1, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
});
</code></pre>

<p>As you might guess, we will need another object. It will be responsible for interaction with our process, i.e.: something that we can ask to &ldquo;exit with code 1.&rdquo; Because we can not ask our process to exit within the test run, we will have to create a spy. And we shall test-drive its functionality. There is something interesting that we should worry about before that - our test suite is passing currently.. but it shouldn&rsquo;t be!</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s step back and think what just happened: clearly, we are writing the test, that can not possibly pass because we do not have <code>ProcessSpy</code> yet. So we are expecting a failure - we are expecting a thrown exception. That expectation is an important part of test-driven development: at all times we expect a very specific failure or we expect our tests to pass; if we do not receive a failure when expected and receive an unexpected failure, we should stop right there and think which part of our thinking and our assumptions is incorrect.</p>

<p><div class="v2-subscribe--inline">
  
  
  
  
  
  


<div class="mc_embed_signup">
  <form action="//tddfellow.us14.list-manage.com/subscribe/post?u=535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34&amp;id=6b61a409a5" method="post" class="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" name="mc-embedded-subscribe-form" class="validate" target="_blank" novalidate>
    <div class="mc_embed_signup_scroll">
      <h3>Would You Like to Watch a Screencast with Me Implementing This?</h3>
      <div class="mc-field-group">
        <!-- real people should not fill this in and expect good things - do not remove this or risk form bot signups-->
        <div style="position: absolute; left: -5000px;" aria-hidden="true"><input type="text" name="b_535a10a8c0274c9a7ebac4f34_6b61a409a5" tabindex="-1" value=""></div>
        <input type="email" value="" name="EMAIL" class="required email mce-EMAIL" placeholder="Enter your email">
        <input type="submit" value="Claim video" name="subscribe" class="button mc-embedded-subscribe">
      </div>
      <div class="">
        <em>(we respect your privacy, unsubscribe at any time)</em>
      </div>
    </div>
  </form>
</div>

</div>
</p>

<p>Right now, tests do not fail, because we are ignoring all exceptions in our <code>try .. catch</code> that we introduced a couple of minutes ago. If we want to see failures again, let&rsquo;s modify <code>catch</code> block to just log all errors it receives:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
    try {
        testSuite[testName]();
    } catch (error) {
        console.log(error);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now our test suite outputs an expected error: <code>ReferenceError: ProcessSpy is not defined</code>. Also, it outputs some other failures that happen in our nested <code>runTestSuite</code> calls - we should fix them by providing <code>silenceFailures</code> option for nested <code>runTestSuite</code> call. We can focus now on the <code>ProcessSpy</code> failure and test-drive it:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">runTestSuite(function ProcessSpy_BehaviorTest(t) {
    var processSpy = new ProcessSpy();
});
// =&gt; ReferenceError: ProcessSpy is not defined

function ProcessSpy() {}
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_initiallyIsNull = function () {
        t.assertEqual(null, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal null, but got: undefined

function ProcessSpy() {
    this.hasExitedWithCode = null;
}
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_isZero_afterExitZeroCall = function () {
        processSpy.exit(0);
        t.assertEqual(0, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; TypeError: processSpy.exit is not a function

// in ProcessSpy
    this.exit = function (code) {
        this.hasExitedWithCode = 0;
    };
// =&gt; PASS

    this.testHasExitedWithCode_isOne_afterExitOneCall = function () {
        processSpy.exit(1);
        t.assertEqual(1, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal 1, but got: 0

// in ProcessSpy
    this.exit = function (code) {
        this.hasExitedWithCode = code;
        // changed 0 to code      ^here^
    };
</code></pre>

<p>I think we have finished test-driving the functionality of <code>ProcessSpy</code>. It is time to get back to our failing test for a failure resulting in an exit with code 1. When we run this test suite, we are getting the following error message: <code>Error: Expected to equal 1, but got: null</code>.&lsquo; To pass this test, we will need to store the fact that we had a failure somewhere and at the end of the test suite run we can trigger exit with code 1 or 0, respectively. We could pass around a <code>status</code> object with boolean property <code>status.failed</code> and set it to <code>true</code> in our <code>catch</code> block:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    } catch (error) {
        if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
        status.failed = true;
    }
</code></pre>

<p>And at the end of <code>runTestSuite</code> function we could call <code>process.exit(1)</code> if <code>status.failed</code> was <code>true</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    // ...

    if (status.failed) {
        process.exit(1);
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>While this works (as in &ldquo;tests pass after providing <code>fakeProcess</code> where needed for nested failing <code>runTestSuite</code> calls&rdquo;) state changes in this code are starting to be hard to follow and function signatures remind me of some horror movie:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
function runTest(testSuite, testName, silenceFailures, status)
function handleTest(reporter, testName, testSuiteConstructor, silenceFailures, status)
function runAllTests(reporter, testSuitePrototype, testSuiteConstructor, silenceFailures, status)
</code></pre>

<p>These signatures smell like objects are hiding there in these functions. Let&rsquo;s find them!</p>

<h2>Quest for hidden objects</h2>

<p>First, let&rsquo;s extract the method object from the function <code>runTestSuite</code>. We will give it a name <code>TestSuiteRunContext</code>:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    options = options || {};
    var reporter = options.reporter || new SimpleReporter();
    var process = options.process || global.process;
    var silenceFailures = options.silenceFailures || false;

    var status = {failed: false};

    var testSuitePrototype = createTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor);

    this.invoke = function () {
        reporter.reportTestSuite(
            getTestSuiteName(testSuiteConstructor, testSuitePrototype)
        );

        runAllTests(
            reporter,
            testSuitePrototype,
            testSuiteConstructor,
            silenceFailures,
            status
        );

        if (status.failed) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    };
}

function runTestSuite(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
    new TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options).invoke();
}
</code></pre>

<p>Now, if we were to move function <code>runAllTests</code> inside of this class, we would not need all these arguments (and all other functions we call):</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    this.invoke = function () {
        reportTestSuite();
        runAllTests();
        finishTestRun();
    };

    function reportTestSuite() {
        reporter.reportTestSuite(getTestSuiteName());
    }

    function getTestSuiteName() {
        if (typeof(createTestSuite().getTestSuiteName) !== "function") {
            return testSuiteConstructor.name;
        }

        return createTestSuite().getTestSuiteName();
    }

    function createTestSuite() {
        return new testSuiteConstructor(assertions);
    }

    function runAllTests() {
        for (var testName in createTestSuite()) {
            if (testName.match(/^test/)) {
                handleTest(testName);
            }
        }
    }

    function handleTest(testName) {
        reportTest(testName);
        runTest(createTestSuite(), testName);
    }

    function reportTest(testName) {
        reporter.reportTest(testName);
    }

    function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
        try {
            testSuite[testName]();
        } catch (error) {
            if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
            status.failed = true;
        }
    }

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.failed) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    }
</code></pre>

<p>It already looks very nice. The only thing that I do not like about this object yet is that it has stateful properties and stateless properties. I like to have my objects separated by this concern. Let&rsquo;s extract <code>status</code> mutable property as a proper <code>TestSuiteRunStatus</code> object:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function TestSuiteRunStatus() {
    var failed = false;

    this.markAsFailed = function () {
        failed = true;
    };

    this.hasFailed = function () {
        return failed;
    };
}

function TestSuiteRunContext(testSuiteConstructor, options) {
  // ...
  var status = new TestSuiteRunStatus();

  // ...
  function runTest(testSuite, testName) {
        try {
            testSuite[testName]();
        } catch (error) {
            if (!silenceFailures) console.log(error);
            status.markAsFailed();
        }
    }

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.hasFailed()) {
            process.exit(1);
        }
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>I think we have finished the refactoring. Now we should verify that test suite exits with the code 0 when everything passes:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">    this.testItExitsWithProcessCodeZero_onSuccess = function () {
        runTestSuite(function (t) {
            this.testFailure = function () {
                t.assertTrue(true);
            };
        }, {process: processSpy, silenceFailures: true});

        t.assertEqual(0, processSpy.hasExitedWithCode);
    };
// =&gt; Error: Expected to equal 0, but got: null

    function finishTestRun() {
        if (status.hasFailed()) return process.exit(1);
        process.exit(0);
    }
// =&gt; PASS
</code></pre>

<h2>Bottom Line</h2>

<p>I think we have finished implementing exit code reporting. The code can be found here: <a href="https://github.com/waterlink/BuildYourOwnTestingFrameworkPart5">https://github.com/waterlink/BuildYourOwnTestingFrameworkPart5</a></p>

<p>There is still a lot to go through. In a few next episodes we will:</p>

<ul>
<li>Report OK and FAIL for each test;</li>
<li>Output carefully formatted failures to the STDERR;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run multiple test suite files at once;</li>
<li>Enable our testing framework to run in a browser (it is javascript after all).</li>
</ul>


<p>Stay tuned!</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don’t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HighScore Kata]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/30/highscore-kata/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-30T18:23:21+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.tddfellow.com/blog/2016/09/30/highscore-kata</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hello, everyone. Today we will take a look into a little problem involving high scores in some sort of game. The game has only one high score and when current game&rsquo;s score exceeds that number, it gets updated. Example acceptance test would read like this:</p>

<p><strong>Given</strong> high score is <code>174</code><br/>
<strong>When</strong> player scores <code>191</code><br/>
<strong>Then</strong> high score is <code>191</code></p>

<!--more-->


<p>Current implementation stores high score in the web browser&rsquo;s local storage. This detail does not change the purpose of this Kata very much since any other platform and language can have its own analog of local storage (file system, in-memory or local database, application settings, etc.). <code>HighScore</code> object looks like this:</p>

<pre><code class="javascript">function Highscore() {
    // initially, load high score value from the local storage
    this.load();
}

Highscore.prototype.updateHighscore = function (score) {
    // check if we need to update high score
    if (score &gt; this.highscore) {
        this.highscore = score;
        this.save();
    }

    // render the high score in the
    // id="highscore" element in the browser
    $("#highscore").text("HIGHSCORE: " + this.highscore);
};

Highscore.prototype.load = function () {
    // localStorage is storing everything as strings,
    // so we need to convert it to number
    this.highscore = parseFloat(localStorage.highscore);
};

Highscore.prototype.save = function () {
    localStorage.highscore = this.highscore;
};
</code></pre>

<p>Task for the Kata:</p>

<ul>
<li>Write tests for this class.</li>
<li>Fix the bug: when a game is launched on the new client (without the high score stored), it renders <code>HIGHSCORE: NaN</code>. (<code>NaN</code> is javascript&rsquo;s abbreviation for &ldquo;not a number&rdquo;). <code>parseFloat</code> most probably is a culprit for this.</li>
<li>Extract storing mechanisms, so that class can be re-used with different storage mechanisms (for example local database, or external REST API).</li>
<li>Make all tests runnable outside of the context of the browser (for example, on <code>nodejs</code>).</li>
</ul>


<p>The focus of this Kata is on architectural boundaries, that this little innocent class spans.</p>

<p>Questions to ask yourself:</p>

<ul>
<li>How much distinct responsibilities this class has?</li>
<li>What architectural boundaries should I draw through this class?

<ul>
<li>How do I split this class according to these boundaries?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What is the easiest way and what is the proper way to make tests runnable outside of the context of the browser?</li>
<li>How would this code look like in different kinds of languages? (static, dynamic, object-oriented, functional, strong-typed, etc.).

<ul>
<li>And how the solution for the Kata will look like for these?</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Next time we will take a look at one possible solution for this Kata. Try to solve it on your own, my dear reader, and please share the code and insights!</p>

<h2>Thanks</h2>

<p>Thank you for reading, my dear reader. If you liked it, please share this article on social networks and follow me on twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>

<p>If you have any questions or feedback for me, don&rsquo;t hesitate to reach me out on Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/waterlink000">@waterlink000</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
